pressures
pressures
GT
GT
retreat
retreat
OK
OK
Go
Go
come tell us about this
來跟我們講解這個
See the world from your phone
從手機看世界
i think we are now
我想我們現在
indeed every day
確實天天
Everyone can't live without their mobile phone
人人大概都離不了手機
So this topic should be of interest to many people.
所以這個題目應該是會引起很多人的
Interest also took the opportunity to learn
興趣也趁機來學習學習
including me
包括我在內
We all say that the older the person, the less likely he is to use the phone
我們都說這個越老的人呢這個手機越不會用
I am one of them so today also
我就是其中之一所以今天也
hope to wait
很希望等候
become
變得
slightly to the phone
對手機稍微
know a little
知道一點
Let me briefly introduce our keynote speaker today
我簡單介紹我們今天主講人的
learning experience
學經歷
that he is
那他是
Department of Information Engineering, National Taiwan University in 1986
臺灣大學資訊工程系1986年的
BS
BS
after graduation
畢業以後
went
去了
Texas A&M
Texas A&M
Texas Austin
Texas Austin
Get a master's and a doctorate in computer science
得到電腦科學系的碩士跟博士
1990 to 1990 and 1994 respectively
分別是1990到1990跟1994
After he came back, he served in the Information Department of National Taiwan University.
回來以後他就在臺大資訊系服務
At present, besides being a member of this hospital, he is also
目前他也是除了是本院的
Director of Capital Innovation Center
資創中心的主任之外
Also Professor of Peace at National Taiwan University
也是臺灣大學的和平教授
Dr. Guo is also currently serving as the vice-chairman of ACM SIGUP
郭博士目前也擔任ACM SIGUP的副主席
Talk to the executive member of the ITREPORTE timely system technical committee
跟ITREPORTE及時系統技術委員會的執行委員
It is the most important executive committee member in the Executive Academy
就是執行學會裡面最主要做事的執行委員
Also served as editor-in-chief and editor-in-chief of many international academic journals
也擔任多國際學術期刊的總編輯跟編輯
Dr. Guo is Kaida and our peace
郭博士除了是凯大和我们和平之外
He is currently a Fellow of ACM and a Fellow of IEEE
他目前也是ACM的Fellow 和IEEE的Fellow
His works have also won the TECO Award
著作等身 也获得过东元奖
It is also regarded as an engineering award in China
国内也算工程方面的大奖
Also received three National Science Council Dismissal Awards
也获得三次的国科会的解除奖
This is the predecessor of the Ministry of Science and Technology
这也就是科技部的前身
Also won the Top Ten Contact Youth of the Republic of China
也获过中华民国十大接触青年
Academia Sinica Young Scholar Book Award
中研院的年轻学者著作奖
I forgot he's actually the youngest of all our directors
我忘记了 他其实是我们所有主任最年轻的
Society of Electrical Engineers Contact Electrical Engineering Professor Award
电机工程学会接触电机工程教授奖
And too big a teaching award, etc.
还有太大的教学奖等等
I won't waste your time anymore
我就不再耽误大家的时间
we are also very much looking forward to
我们也非常期待
Can get a little more information in the future
可以在未來的時間多得一點訊息
Thanks
謝謝
please
請
Thank you very very much Vice President
非常非常謝謝副院長
When the vice president asked me to talk about a topic?
當副院長要我來講個題目的時候呢
I just thought of what to say best
我就想到講什麼最好
Because the phone is always on
因為手機不離聲
I just thought that this machine is in my hand, hope is endless
我就想到這一機在手希望無窮
OK
OK
So let’s talk about viewing the world from your mobile phone
所以就講從手機看世界
Well, this topic
那其實這一個題目
I was once in a popular science speech
我曾經在一個科普的演講裡面
slightly mentioned
稍微提過
If you have seen
各位如果看過的話
Take what you have heard as a review
聽過的話就當作複習
Of course everyone has a cell phone
那當然大家都有手機
Everyone says why smartphones are smart
大家都說智慧型手機為什麼智慧
people often ask this question
大家常常問這個問題
So what's the difference with the previous mobile phone?
那跟以前手機到底有什麼不一樣
Then I want to look at it from this angle
那我想就從這個角度來去看這件事情
See the world from your phone
從手機來看這個世界
If you look at the world from your mobile phone
那從手機來看這個世界的話
I'm bound to talk about the phone and what's around it
我勢必就要談手機跟它四周的東西
so therefore
所以因此呢
Here I choose to speak with Android
在這裡我選擇用Android來講
Because Android has the highest market share
因為Android的市佔率是最高的
80% of all mobile phones equals 82%
有80%的 等於82%所有的手機
are so-called Android phones
都是所謂的Android的手機
So from the perspective of Android
所以從Android來講這件事情
So let's talk about Android and its environment
所以我們講Android跟它的環境
Of course when it comes to this
當然講到這個的時候
we'll look back
我們就回過頭來看
Why is it called a smartphone
為什麼叫智慧型手機
isn't it just a mobile phone
它不就是一支手機嗎
let's just call
讓我們來打電話而已
Why is it called a smartphone
為什麼叫做智慧型手機
Remember everyone will find out
記得大家就會發現
I actually do a lot of things on my phone
其實我在手機上做的事情很多
That seems to answer all kinds of questions I have.
那好像可以回答我各式各樣的問題
so i think it's a smartphone
所以我覺得它是一個智慧型手機
In that case maybe we should see
那這樣的話也許我們應該看
This so-called smart phone
這個所謂智慧型手機
what's behind
背後到底有什麼東西
can bring us these wisdom
能夠帶給我們這些智慧
Of course everyone said
那當然大家都說
what if that's the case
那如果是這樣子的話呢
I should be more and more established
我應該會越來越成立
or use my phone
或是使用我的手機
Everything is on my phone
所有東西都放在我的手機上面
like me now
就像我現在
I listen to music on my phone
我音樂都是用手機在聽的
What about taking pictures?
那照相呢
In fact, most of the photos I took are also on my mobile phone.
其實照的照片大部分也都在手機
i think most of you here
我想在座大部分人
They must be taking pictures with their cell phones.
應該都是用手機在照相
well maybe so
好 可能是這樣
I am like this
我自己是這樣子的
I stopped buying cameras many years ago
很多年前我就不再買照相機了
because my cell phone works fine
因為我的手機很好用
After I finished taking the photo, he uploaded it directly to the Internet.
我照完之後他就直接上傳到網路去
and it's easy to share with others
而且很容易分享給別人
I can use that
我用那也好
these different messaging programs
這些不同的訊息服務程式
I can send it to anyone
我就可以傳送給任何一個人
perfectly worked
非常好用
Of course, after Shu Bodong got on the phone
那當然舒伯東就上了手機之後
you should ask a question
你應該問一個問題
Will he be like my personal computer one day
他會不會有一天像我個人電腦一樣
There is a virus in
有病毒進去
one day when you open
有一天你打開的時候
he appears blue
他出現藍色畫面
you can't make phone calls
你就不能打手機了
what to do
那怎麼辦
or
或是說呢
I put all my stuff on my phone
我把我所有東西都放到手機上面去了
one day he told you
有一天他告訴你說
Sorry, the address book is gone
對不起 通訊錄已經沒有了
do you feel panicked
那你會不會覺得很驚慌
I think everyone has this problem
我想大家都會有這樣的問題
that's not all
那不只是這樣子
When Shu Bodong got on the phone
當舒伯東就上了手機之後
Everyone is like me, I carry my mobile phone with me every day
大家跟我一樣 我每天帶著手機
Every morning when I go out without my mobile phone
每天早上出門沒帶手機
I feel weird today
我好像覺得今天怪怪的
That's not true, everyone
那各位其實不然
you will find many things
你會發現很多事情
Began to connect more and more with the mobile phone
開始越來越跟手機連在一起了
why do you feel a little flustered
為什麼你會覺得有一點慌亂
if you do not have
如果你沒有
go out without a mobile phone
沒帶手機出門
now because
現在是因為
This is how other people contact you
別人都用這樣的方式來聯繫你
You use these methods to quickly send some text messages to people
你用這些方式很快跟人家傳送一些短訊
so convenient
所以很方便
Slowly you may find that
慢慢你可能會發現說
You will become more and more dependent on your mobile phone
你會越來越依賴手機
Why
為什麼
Everyone has heard of the Internet of Things, right?
大家都聽過物聯網對不對
Internet of Everything
萬物聯網
What things will be connected to the Internet?
哪些東西會聯網呢
In fact, you can imagine the future
其實未來各位可以想像
your glasses
你的眼鏡
It's like the Google glasses you see, right?
就像各位看到的Google眼鏡對不對
Many people will wear all kinds of things in the future
很多人身上以後會配戴各式各樣的東西
always like your current logger
總於像你現在的記錄器
There are still many things you will hang on your body in the future
未來還有很多東西你會掛在身上
even wear it
甚至穿在身上
At this time, you will find that you don’t leave your mobile phone anymore
這時候你會發現手機你越來越不離開它了
because everything is connected
因為萬物相連
after everything is connected
萬物相連之後
I ask you
我請問你
Would you like to pay a phone bill per device
你願意每一個裝置都付一筆電話費用嗎
of course not right
當然不會對不對
In the end, everything can be sent to your mobile phone
最後所有東西可能到你的手機再送出去
So when you don't have your phone
所以手機沒帶的時候
I believe you will be more anxious
我相信各位會更焦慮
ok there is no way
好 這是沒有辦法
because
因為呢
This is some further development
這就是再往下的一些發展
So I want to take this opportunity today
所以我今天想藉著這個機會
We watched it all the way from the phone
我們從手機一路看下去
See what this idea of ​​the future of IoT could look like
看到未來物聯網的這個想法會是什麼樣子
Everyone look at your phone
各位來看手機
Do you guys only have a cell phone to call?
各位手機只有哪來打電話嗎
Believers raise hands
相信的人舉手
No, no, no one believes, right?
沒有對不對 沒有人相信對不對
Can a computer make phone calls before?
以前電腦可以打電話嗎
The computer can't make phone calls, right?
電腦不能打電話對不對
Since the beginning of the so-called video telephony
自從開始有所謂的視訊電話之後
The computer starts to make phone calls
電腦開始變成可以打電話了
then you find one thing
那你發現一件事情
Computers used to do these calculations and data processing for me
電腦以前幫我做這些計算 資料 處理
i can surf the internet i can shop
我可以上網 我可以購物
can play electric toys
可以打電動玩具
Mobile phones seem to be able to do this now.
現在手機好像也都可以做這件事情
So therefore you start to have an idea
所以因此你開始出現一個想法
The world of mobile phones and computers has actually begun to integrate
手機跟電腦世界其實開始整合了
these two things put together
這兩個東西整在一起
In the past, we applied to the telecom company for a door number
以前我們向電信公司申請門號
receive his telecommunications service
接受他的電信服務
And these telecommunications services from
而這些電信服務從
From domestic calls, long-distance calls, international calls, transferred conference calls, etc.
從國內的電話 長途的電話 國際的電話 轉接的電話會議等等
These are the services provided by the telecommunications company to you.
都是電信公司提供給你的服務
what about now you start to think about it
那現在呢 你開始想一想
seems different
好像不太一樣
What about my phone company, whether it's Chunghwa Telecom or Taiwan Mobile?
我的電話公司呢 不管是中華電信 台灣大哥大
It seems that it is not the same as before
好像跟以前也不太一樣
not like a phone company
不像是一家電話公司
Fast glasses that function as smartphones
隨著智慧型手機的功能快速的眼鏡
Internet access has become very convenient
上網變得非常非常的方便
you also noticed one thing
你也注意到一件事情
It seems that the world of the Internet and the world of telecommunications have begun to merge
網路的世界跟電信的世界好像也開始融合了
The formerly so-called world of telecommunications
以前所謂的電信的世界
It's as if we call the phone company that provides our service
就好像我們打電話 電話公司提供我們的服務
It is they who provide us with the contact method of telecommunications
是他們提供我們電信這一個聯絡的方式
The Internet used to belong to our computers only.
網路呢 以前好像只屬於我們的電腦
Now what about these telecommunications companies that provide you with Internet access
現在呢 這些電信公司它提供讓你網路上網
It also provides your telecommunications services from now on
它從此也提供你電信的服務
Then you will find that there are some so-called
接著你就會發現 有一些所謂的
This Internet company, he also started a telecommunications company business
這個網路的公司 他也開始做起電信公司的生意
Of course this means
當然這代表
what's starting to come together
什麼東西呢 開始融合在一起
In addition, your mobile phone is no longer a phone call.
另外你手機上面其實已經不是打電話了
Think about how many things you do on your phone
各位想想看你有多少事情在手機上面做
let me ask you first
我先請問各位
Everyone, you want to know the weather this morning
各位你想知道今天早上的天氣
Or if it rains, how many people check the computer
或者有沒有下雨 有多少人查電腦
How many people look at their mobile phones
多少人看手機
I look at my phone OK
我看手機 OK
Many people look at their phones, right?
很多人都看手機對不對
Because it's so convenient that everything is on top
因為太方便了 所有東西都在上面
OK there are all kinds of software on it
OK 上面有各式各樣的軟體
You can download and use
你可以下載來使用
In the past you had to find a software
以前你要找到一個軟體
Is it troublesome to install it on your computer?
裝到你的電腦上面 是不是很麻煩
You need someone to pretend for you, right?
你要找人幫你裝對不對
now you have an android phone
現在你有一支安卓手機
or you have an iPhone
或是你有一支iPhone的手機
you need to install new software
你要裝新的軟體
Many of you may come to his
各位很多人可能就到他的
His so-called market
他的所謂的這個market
or play a different site
或是play不同的網站
directly downloaded
直接就下載了
one click and it will come down
點一下就下來了
So actually
所以其實呢
Everything seems to be very, very convenient
所有東西看起來好像都變得非常非常便利
Everything starts to concentrate on your phone
所有東西開始集中到你這支手機上面去了
Extremely convenient to use
使用上變得異常的便利
so we'll look back
所以我們就回過頭來看
What are you using your phone for?
手機到底拿來幹嘛
Let’s give a few examples of an application that everyone sees very often.
我們舉幾個大家很常看的一個應用
For example, if you say
譬如說各位如果說
you need to check the map
你要查地圖
you will find out
你會發現呢
If according to some of our past data
如果根據我們過去的一些資料
you can tell
你可以看出來
most people are on mobile
大部分人是在手機上
The blue part is the mobile phone
藍色的部分是手機
The orange part is the computer
這個橘色的部分是電腦
Most people just look up the map
大部分人只要查地圖
I actually checked it on my phone.
其實是在手機上查的
The weather is also on the phone
天氣也在手機上
Listen to music on your phone
聽音樂也在手機上
you and others are using some facebook
你跟人家在用一些facebook
In fact, many people have also gone to the mobile phone
其實很多人也到手機上面去了
If you don't believe me, go home and see your children
不信你回家看你們家的孩子
where to go to facebook
在哪裡上facebook
so you will find
所以你會發現
Actually a lot of work
其實很多工作呢
what we used to do on the computer
我們以往在電腦上做的
Slowly all moved to the mobile phone
慢慢全部都移到手機上面去了
because it's so convenient
因為它太方便
And it has so many functions
而且它的功能太多了
OK
OK
good
好
of course
那當然呢
from this point of view
從這角度來看
let's ask another question
我們再來問另外一個問題
OK
OK
I want to address these so-called
我要對這些所謂的
For mobile phone users
手機的用戶來說
what jobs are you looking for
哪些工作你會在搜尋
do it on top or look at it from another angle
在上面做 或從另外的角度來看
you will notice
你會注意到
I want to send some messages to someone
我要送一些訊息給別人
I'm 90% on my phone
我90%全部都在手機
Just like you are using Line
就像各位在用Line一樣
Or work with your Messenger etc.
或用你的Messenger等等這些工作
ok photos
OK 照片
you are not the only ones
各位不是唯一的
83% of people do the same thing as you
83%的人跟你做一樣的事情
send email?
送Email呢
Many people also do it on mobile phones
很多人也是在手機上面做的
There are many, many jobs that do this
還有很多很多工作都是這樣做的
And of course there's a tablet, right?
當然還有平板電腦對不對
Of course, the tablet is also a big usage environment.
當然平板電腦也是一個很大的一個使用環境
Of course you can find out
那當然各位可以發現
a lot of searches
很多搜尋呢
Some things will still be done on the tablet
有些東西還會在平板電腦上面做
Why because the screen is bigger
為什麼 因為螢幕比較大
OK good
OK 好
But what?
可是呢
Everyone, the world will gradually change
各位這世界會逐漸的改變
OK, let's look at it from another angle
OK 那我們再從另外一個角度來看
how to use mobile phone how to use mobile phone
如何來使用手機 怎麼用手機
Guys, let's look at it from two angles
各位 我們從兩個角度來看
what if
如果說呢
You're using a browser on your phone to search for something
你在手機上使用一個瀏覽器在搜尋東西
Looking for information OK
在找資料 OK
what kind of work is done on it
那有哪些工作在上面做
what did you watch
你大概看了哪些東西
Of course you have something here
當然各位這邊有一些東西是
Like Google, Facebook, etc.
像Google、Facebook等等
This is done with Browseing
這個是在用Browseing來做
But I have to say on the phone
可是呢 我必須要講 在手機上面呢
because it has a small screen
因為它螢幕很小
In fact, what do most people use
其實大部分人是用什麼
In fact, most people use RUN App
其實大部分人是用RUN App
These so-called applications
這些所謂的應用程式
What about the app?
應用程式上 應用程式呢
In fact, like Facebook, Facebook, etc.
其實像Facebook、臉書等等
are the most used
都是使用率最高的東西
Okay, of course we're here
好 那當然講到這兒呢
You should probably agree
各位應該大概都會同意
You do a lot on your phone
你在手機上的確做了非常多的事情
Then let's first define what is called App
那我們先來定義什麼叫做App
What is an application
什麼叫應用程式
What about the application, the so-called App
應用程式呢 所謂的App
refers to the smartphone
指的是在智慧型手機
on tablet
平板電腦上
or even on some mobile devices
或甚至一些行動裝置上
some apps used
使用的一些應用程式
We call it App
我們稱為App
OK
OK
Well, if you have an app, someone will sell your app
好 那有App就有人要賣你App
OK so all these apps
OK 所以這些所有的App
There are so-called App stores
就有所謂的App的商店
Just like you can see in Apple
就像各位看到在Apple也好
Or even in Taiwan Mobile
或在甚至台灣大哥大也好
They all have these apps
他們都有這些App
OK
OK
well that
好 那
The so-called store of these apps
所謂這些App的商店
It allows mobile device users
它可以讓行動裝置使用者
Internet via Wi-Fi
透過無線上網
An app connected to a mobile network
連上行動網路的一個應用
store for this app
這個程式的商店
Download your program for free or for a fee
免費或是付費下載你的程式
Then it's easy to put on it
然後很容易就裝到上面去了
Then these so-called App stores
那這些所謂的App的商店
In the beginning, of course, it was Apple
一開始當然出來是Apple
A year later, Google came out with
過一年之後 Google也出了
Of course there will be more and more
那當然就越來越多了
First App Store
一開始App Store
when it was founded by apple
由蘋果公司創立的時候
It's not just for the iPhone
它不只是給iPhone
Your iPad Touch
你的iPad Touch
And these larger tablets for the iPad
還有這些iPad比較大的平板電腦
so that everyone can publish
在上面讓大家能夠發佈
and be able to download these associated programs
而且能夠下載這些相關的程式
Then of course anyone starts to feel that
那當然任何一個人也開始覺得說
Then I can also write my App
那我也可以把我的App寫出來
I upload and I can also sell it to others
我上傳我也可以賣給別人
So it’s not just about downloading and using
所以其實不是只有下載來做使用
It also makes selling easier
也讓銷售變得更加的簡單
you can go up directly
你直接就可以上去
anyone can put something
誰都可以把東西
It's easy to sell to someone in another corner of the world
很容易賣給世界上另外一個角落的人
So many things changed accordingly
所以因此很多東西就跟著改變
What app stores are there?
那有哪些App的商店呢
For example, Apple's App Store
譬如說Apple的App Store
And there's Google's called Play
還有Google的叫做Play
they all have a name
他們都取了一個名字
Windows is called Phone Store
Windows的叫做Phone Store
The so-called black media machine
那所謂的黑媒機
Blackberry also has its
Blackberry也有它的
and Amazon's
還有Amazon的
and Samsung
還有Samsung的
Of course not only these things
當然不只這些東西
Let's say this is Windows
譬如說這是Windows
This is Apple's App Store
這是Apple的App Store
Then everyone can upload it
那大家都可以把它上傳
Of course if you want to upload
那當然你要上傳的話
Inside Apple he asked to say
在Apple裡面他要求說
you have to pay the annual fee
你要付這個年費
He usually pays about 99 dollars a year
他一般來說一年大概付99塊美金
I can become his member
我就可以成為他的會員
if i want to upload something
我東西要上傳的話
he has to check first
他必須要先審查
then you can download
那你才可以下載
If he sells you something for 100 bucks
如果他賣了你100塊的東西的話
He wants to draw 30 yuan
他要抽30塊
Of course the developer
那當然這個開發者
You can get 70 yuan
就可以拿到70塊
ok of course
好 那當然
The 30 yuan he claimed was for maintenance and other expenses
30塊他宣稱是來做維護等等這些費用
Not only Apple
不只Apple
Of course, Google will also join the battle soon
當然很快Google也立刻加入戰場
He is now called Google Play
他現在叫做Google Play
also the same
也是一樣
But Google is a little different
不過Google有點不一樣
Where is it?
在哪裡呢?
Google says I only charge you once
Google說我只收你一次錢
like 25 dollars
好像25塊美金
It can be used for life from now on
從此以後 終身都可以使用
you don't have to pay me every year
你不用每年付我錢
But Google has another idea
不過Google還有一個想法
He said that anyone can upload and anyone can download
他說誰都可以上去 誰都可以下載
But of course you imagine
不過當然各位這樣想像
if it is like this
如果是這樣的話
you have an app
你有一個App
It is easier for you to upload
你比較容易上傳
Of course bad guys can upload
當然壞人也能夠上傳
so what does it mean
所以表示什麼
Everyone throws things up
大家都把東西倒上去
Then you can just pull the thing down and use it
那你把東西拉下來就可以用
will you be poisoned
你會不會中毒
Wait, these problems may follow
等等這些問題也許就跟著出現
Of course it's the other way around
那當然倒過來就是
if someone censored
如果有人審查的話
You say it's safer
各位說比較安全
But the problem is more troublesome
可是帶來的問題就是比較煩
You have waited for a long time and haven't put it on the shelves
你等了很久都沒有上架
even sometimes doubt
甚至有時候懷疑
Apple may have deliberately kept him out of the shelves
Apple可能故意不讓他上架
because he might be doing something like that
因為他可能在做類似的一些工作
Of course these are all possible predictions
當然這都是可能的預測
Not only that, he also does Windows
不只這樣 Windows他也做
Just like you guys on your Windows tablet
就像各位在 Windows的平板上面
Now even on your PC
現在甚至你的個人電腦上
You put Windows 8, Windows 10
你把Windows 8、Windows 10
You can download it in his App Store
你都可以下載 在他App Store
can download some of your software
可以下載你的一些軟體
installed on your computer
裝在你的這個電腦上面
And of course your phone
當然還包括你的手機上面
more than that
不只這樣子
Taiwan's telecom operators also want to count this business
台灣的電信業者也想算這個生意
So the telecom operator also provided him with the App Store
所以電信業者他也提供給他App Store
You can also download your stuff
你也可以下載你的東西
Like Chunghwa Telecom doing this Hami
就像中華電信做這個Hami
Of course, Yuanchuan also does this.
當然遠傳也做這件事
you can imagine
你可以想像
If this is the case, of course the Taiwan Revolutionary Committee will also do this.
如果這樣台灣大革大當然也幹這件事
OK
OK
Do you only have telecom companies doing this?
各位只有電信公司做這件事嗎
of course not
當然不是的
OK
OK
Of course what else is included?
當然還有包括哪些呢
Including mobile phones like Samsung
包括像三星做手機的
he also wants to do this business
他也想做這個生意
Bigger wants to sell things
越大都想賣東西
OK
OK
good
好
Let's compare a little bit with these so-called App Store
我們稍微比較一下這些所謂的App Store
you can see
各位可以看到
Whether it is Apple or
不管是Apple也好
Windows is also good
Windows也好
Google is also good
Google也好
Or Chunghwa Telecom, Far EasTone, etc.
或是說中華電信 遠傳等等
They both serve different operating systems
他們都服務不同的作業系統
like some like this one
像有的 像這一個
This may be Taiwan's Big Brother
這可能是台灣大哥大
He basically said that there are many service providers
他基本上 他講服務的廠商就很多
Not just Windows
不只是Windows
and including Apple's
還有包括Apple的
Also includes Android
還有包括Android
they all have different ideas
他們都有不同的一些想法
to compete with each other in the market
來在市場上跟互相做競爭
But they all have a share
不過他們都要分一杯羹
because he could be a good source of profit
因為他可能是一個很好的獲利來源
There is an App Store
有App Store
from above
大家就可以從上面
Many apps can be downloaded for use
可以下載很多App來做使用
of course like this
當然 就這樣子
before i go on
我在往下講之前
I'll go back and do a little more with you guys.
我先回過頭來跟各位再做一點
Introduce the idea of ​​Android
介紹Android的想法
and its environment
還有它的環境
Let's look at what's behind it
我們再來看它背後的東西
Do you have any questions?
各位有任何問題
Welcome to ask questions or click me
歡迎各位發問或是我點一下
Let's answer together later
等一下再一起來回答
Ok Android what is Android?
好 Android 什麼是 Android?
Android is an open source
Android 是一個開放原始碼的
open source operating system
在以開放原始碼作業系統
A Linux-based platform
Lenux 為基礎的一個平台
So its bottom layer is a Linux operating system
所以它最底層是個Lenux的作業系統
It has some environment on it
那上面它有一些環境
so we call it a platform
因此我們叫它叫作一個平台
what to say now
那現在來說的話
Google's entire ecosystem
Google 這整個生態系
resulting action platform
所產生的行動平台
fastest growing in the world
全世界成長最快
It now holds about 82% of a market
它現在佔據了大概 82% 的一個市場
Of course it's not just the phone.
那當然不是只有手機啊
you should notice
各位應該注意到
including some TV platforms like
包括一些電視像這樣的平台
There are many starting to adopt Android
有很多開始採用 Android
ok that's natural
好 那這是自然的
Then everyone will say come down again
那大家會說那再下來呢
It's not just your phone
其實不只是你的手機
not just your tv
不只是你的電視
You should also notice that Apple and Google
各位應該也注意到 Apple 跟 Google
want to sell stuff to put on your car
都想賣東西裝在你的車上
OK, of course it's not just like that
OK 當然也不只是這樣子
After doing some business and thinking about wearing fashion later
在做一些生意 想以後穿戴時裝之
Is there any way how to make a connection with him?
有沒有辦法怎麼跟他做一個連線
Okay, let's talk about this topic later.
好 之後後面再來談這個議題
Of course, this is just to give you a feeling.
那當然各位這只是給各位一個感覺
Underneath is the core of a Linux operating system
底下是一個 Linux 作業系統的核心
Above the whole thing Android
上面整個東西 Android
They thought of this set of things to put on top of this core
他們想了這一套東西放在這個核心的上面
different developers
讓不同的開發商
has its different roles to play
有它不同的角色可以扮演
For example, some developers in Taiwan
譬如說台灣有一些開發商
he does some hardware stuff
他做某一些硬體的東西
He can stuff relevant things into this Korean library
他就可以把相關的東西塞進這個韓式庫
It can be easily plugged into the whole system.
就很容易可以塞到整個體系裡面去
Of course, this forms an entire ecosystem on top of it.
那當然這形成一個整個生態系在上面
well that
好 那
Let me first tell you what an operating system is
我先跟各位報告什麼叫作業系統
The operating system is when you turn on the computer
作業系統就是你打開電腦之後
just kept running
就一直在跑
The program that ends after you shut down is called the operating system
跑到你關機之後結束的程式就叫作業系統
Just like the operating system on your personal computer is Windows
就像各位在個人電腦上的作業系統就是 Windows
OK
OK
That's on your phone Android
那在你的手機上 Android
is your platform
就是你的平台
The whole platform runs on it
上面整個平台在上面跑
OK
OK
In other words
那換句話說呢
It is an environment between our users and the hardware
它是介於我們使用者跟硬體之間的一個環境
All hardware it controls
它控制的所有硬體
Services that provide all our stuff
提供給我們所有東西的服務
that's up there
那在上面呢
you can directly manipulate it
你可以直接操作它
You can also run some apps on it
你也可以用一些應用程式在上面跑
Let everyone see some different APPs
就讓各位看到一些不同的APP
OK
OK
Or those who see you running
或是各位看你跑的這些
This Word Powerpoint and so on these software
這個Word Powerpoint等等這些軟體
well these are
好這些都是
what about these things
這些東西呢
application software
就叫應用軟體
it runs on top of the operating system
它跑在作業系統上面
The operating system directly controls your hardware
作業系統直接控制你的硬體
What is the mainstream operating system now?
那主流的作業系統現在是什麼呢
what about the first one
第一個呢
Of course Unix and Linux series
當然Unix跟Linux這個系列
What about Linux?
Linux呢
I just reported to you
就是剛跟各位報告了
The operating system running under Android
在Android下面跑的那個作業系統
OK
OK
then it's an open source
那它是一個開放原始碼
Wait a minute and I'll report to you
等一下我跟各位報告
What is Open Source
什麼叫開放原始碼
OK
OK
Then they belong to a similar series
那它們是屬於類似的系列的
We say the series of Unix and Linux
我們說Unix和Linux的系列
And Unix
而Unix呢
At Bell
當初是在Bell
Developed at Bell Laboratories
在貝爾實驗室發展出來
Developed from 1971 to 73
在1971年到73年發展出來的
Then began to produce some branches
後來就開始產生一些分支
in 1977
在1977年的時候呢
There is another branch called Berkeley Distribution
又出現了一個分支叫Berkeley的Distribution
A fork of Berkeley's version of this
伯克萊的一個分支的這個版本
And these things are called open source
而這些東西呢都所謂的開放原始碼
First of all what is open source
首先什麼叫開放原始碼
Open source is the software
開放原始碼就是這些軟體呢
It's written down this program it must be open
它的寫下這個程式呢必須要開放
able to spread freely
能夠自由的散佈
Basically its spirit is like this
就基本它的精神是這樣子的
Mocking Touch's Always is made by Apple companies
Mocking Touch的Always就各位Apple公司做的
This is another mainstream operating system
這是另外一個主流的作業系統
Another one is that you are very common
還有一個就是各位非常常用
Windows commercial operating system on personal computers
個人電腦上的Windows的商用作業系統
Alright then let's move on to Lenax
好那我們再來繼續來看Lenax
Because it is the most important core under Android
因為它是在Android下面最重要的核心
Lenax was actually a student at the time
Lenax呢其實是當初分軟的一個學生
He thinks these are used in class
他覺得呢在課堂上用的這些
The homework system used for teaching is really bad
教學用的作業系統實在太爛了
So he read a book and made one
所以他看著書就做了一個出來
From now on everyone will be fine
從此以後大家就會挺好的
I just started adding things in.
就開始一直加東西進去
The first version was in 1991
那第一個版本是在1991年
Published on the Internet in September
9月發佈在互聯網上面
Since then, everyone has continued to add things to it.
從此以後大家不斷的加東西在上面
more prosperous
越來越豐興
we just knew
我們剛剛都知道
Lenix it is at the bottom of the whole Android
Lenix它在整個Android裡面最下面
It hosts the entirety of our Android operating system
它承載了整個我們的安卓作業系統
Under the hood it's basically an open software operating system
那底下它基本上是一個開放軟體的作業系統
OK good
OK 好
Then I will introduce one more thing to you now.
那我現在跟各位再介紹一個東西
Called Open Handset Alliance
叫Open Handset Alliance
OK a coalition of so-called open handsets
OK 所謂的開放手持裝置的一個聯盟
What is the Alliance for Open Handheld Devices?
什麼叫開放手持裝置的聯盟
In fact, this thing is launched by Google
其實這個東西是Google所推出來的
Because why is Google launching this thing
因為Google為什麼要推出這個東西
Google it's very smart
Google它非常聰明
OK Google says I'm going to do this business now
OK Google說我現在要做這個生意
What should I do with Windows
我跟Windows應該怎麼打
Windows said how much I would sell you for an operating system
Windows說我一個作業系統賣你多少錢
He said I don't need money OK
他說我不用錢 OK
But what money does he earn from you?
可是他賺你什麼錢
he earns advertising money
他賺廣告的錢
OK
OK
Because once the operating system without money
因為一旦不用錢的作業系統
Let's do it together
武力大家一起來做
After making these phones?
做出了這些手機之後呢
Sowen
大家上網做搜尋的搜紋
All the traffic flows to my Google
就流量通通流到我Google來
'Cause everyone's coming to me
因為所有人都流到我這邊來
I know what you want to do
我就知道你們想幹什麼
And you are on my network
而且呢你上了我這個網
I'll show you the ad
我就給你看廣告
I just pay advertisers
我就給廣告商收錢
so therefore
所以因此呢
He told you no money
他跟你講不用錢
Because he takes money from others
因為他跟別人收錢
OK
OK
What about Windows?
那Window呢
he wants to sell you this thing
他想賣給你這個東西
I found out that your things don't cost money
就發現你的東西不用錢
So of course Window is in trouble
所以當然Window就出了麻煩
That
那
Google wants to do this business
Google想做這個生意
Of course he can't do it by himself.
他自己一個人當然做不來啊
So he told a bunch of people
所以他找一堆人說
Let's make a mobile phone together
我們一起來做手機
make money together
一起來賺錢
So he formed this organization
所以他就成立這個組織
A Consortium of Open Handsets
開放手持裝置的一個聯盟
He organized such an alliance
他就組織這麼一個聯盟
just say
就說
Telecom provider Mobile phone provider
電信商 手機商
do hardware
做硬體的
all together
大家一起來
let's make a phone
我們來做手機
my operating system is free
我的作業系統不用錢
OK let's do it together
OK 大家一起來做
That quickly assembled dozens of companies
那很快就集結了幾十個公司
That sounds good, of course, right?
那當然說得很好聽對不對
But he wants to make money in the end
不過他最後就是要賺錢
OK of course this so-called this
OK 當然這個所謂的這個
This open hand holds this alliance
這個開放手持裝這個聯盟
he has a great mission
他有一個很偉大的使命
He said he hoped to make a better mobile phone
他說呢 他希望能夠做一個比較好的手機
to our users
給我們的使用者
And everything is open
而且呢 所有東西都是開放的
OK
OK
And what if you have any vision
而且呢 如果呢 你有任何願景
we'll make it happen
我們就把它實現
just his basic idea
只是他基本的想法
OK, smart, right?
OK 很聰明吧 OK
So, a lot of people started to struggle to come together and do it together.
所以呢 很多人開始糾結過來 一起來做
Telecom providers include telecom providers in various places at home and abroad
電信商呢 包括國內外各個地方的電信商
OK, some of you have also seen OK
OK 各位有些也看過 OK
Including this everyone see this T-Mobile in the US
包括這個各位看到這T-Mobile在美國
Very European Vodafone
非常歐洲的Bodafone
Or on the mainland, China Mobile, etc.
或是在大陸這個中國移動等等
Handset for mobile phones
Handset 做手機的
Like our Acer and other companies
就像我們的Acer 等等這些公司
Or chip companies like ARM
或是做晶片的 像 ARM這些公司
Or software companies like Google Ibe, etc.
或是做軟體的像Google 伊貝等等這些公司
Or do some commercial companies
或是做包括一些商業化的公司
For example, the companies he consults with
譬如說他做顧問的這些公司
Everyone tangled together to make a mobile phone together
大家糾結在一起 一起來做手機
OK, that's of course very smart.
OK 好 那當然非常聰明
soon to be a fad
很快就造成風潮
swept the market very quickly
非常快速就席捲這個市場
Because everyone in this ecosystem
因為每一個人在這生態系裡面
can have a share
都可以分一杯羹
OK so everyone come in and do it
OK 所以大家就進來做
So after everyone has done
所以大家都做了之後呢
Sure enough, a lot of traffic flows into Google
果然大量的流量就流進Google
OK then they make a lot of money
OK 那他們就賺了很多錢
OK his basic story goes like this
OK 他基本的故事是這樣玩
OK, then I just mentioned
OK 好 那我剛剛各位提到
Lenix is ​​also good
Lenix也好
Android is also good
Android也好
It's an open source concept
它是一個開放原始碼的概念
open that is
開放也就是說
I bring this thing, I can change it
這個東西我拿來 我可以改
I should give it to someone else after I'm done
我弄完之後我應該給別人
OK so the concept of open source
OK 所以開放原始碼的概念
that I'm free to walk again
就是我可以自由再散步
Besides, you write a program
而且呢 你這個寫程式出來
You have to give me this code
這個程式碼你要給我
After I finish writing, I also want to give it to others
我寫完之後我也要給別人
OK, so what did you change at this time?
OK 那這時候你改完的東西呢
must also remain open
也必須繼續是開放的
i want to be able to walk
我要能夠散步
And I can't stipulate that he can only be exclusive to a certain
而且我不能夠把他規定說只能專屬在某一個
For example, a mobile phone or a tablet
譬如說手機還是平板
then this thing must be complete
那這東西必須要完整
And I can't restrict you to do this program with other programs
而且我不能限制你這個程式跟別的程式一起做
I can't take a walk because of that.
就因此不能散步 也不行
Your stuff still needs to be able to walk
你的東西還是要能夠散步
The various ways of walking must be handled with skill
各式各樣的散步的方式必須技術中理
This means that both electronic files and written files should be able to walk
意思就是說電子檔 書面檔都要能夠散步
So it's a free walk
所以是完全的自由散步
Its concept is like this
它的概念是這個樣子
Open source code means that everyone can see it
開放原始碼也就是說開放大家都可以看
does not mean free
並不代表免費
If you don't understand, you can still ask me to collect money for you
你如果看不懂要問我還是可以給你收錢的
because I offer you my knowledge
因為我提供我的知識給你
So I think openness and free are two different things
所以我想開放跟免費是兩件事情
open just saying i can show you
開放只是說我可以給你看
you can also watch
你也可以看
You don't understand what's going on in your house
你看不懂那你家的事
Of course, after opening up, it will be a very important change.
那當然有開放之後就是一個很重要的改變
Because once it's open source
因為一旦是開放原始碼之後
In fact, the industry is booming
其實讓這產業非常蓬勃的發展
This knowledge also flows quickly
這知識也快速的流動
Of course, it is also very good for Taiwan.
當然對台灣也是很有好處的
Because it used to be 20 years ago
因為以往在20年前呢
The so-called operating system is a great technology
所謂的作業系統是很偉大的科技
Because everyone doesn't know how to write
因為大家都不知道怎麼寫
It's everywhere now, isn't it?
現在到處都是 對不對
everyone knows how to write
大家都知道怎麼寫
Everyone knows how to change
大家都知道怎麼改
Of course not only operating systems have open source
當然不是只有作業系統是有開放原始碼
There's a lot more open source
還有很多東西開放原始碼
Give me some examples
各位舉幾個例子
For example, as a window interface
譬如說做視窗界面的
or even you stay soft
或甚至你留軟氣的
Some people use FarFox which is a soft gas
有人用FarFox 這是一個留軟氣
or even some challenges with Microsoft Office
或甚至有一些挑戰微軟的Office
The so-called OpenOffice
所謂的OpenOffice
or even the database's
或甚至資料庫的
data transfer software
資料傳輸軟體的
There are also so-called web servers
還有所謂的網頁伺服器
All kinds of things are open
各式各樣東西都是Open的
There are many companies you also find that say
有很多公司你也發現說
I don't do it my way anymore
我不要再用我自己的做法
If a lot of people open source
如果有很多人開放原始碼
People keep adding new things
不斷有人加新的東西進去
I'll just take part in their calculations
我乾脆參加他們的算
if that thing does well
如果那東西做得很好
I'll use his stuff and continue to enhance it
我就用他的東西再繼續把它增強
Anyway, if things are bad, someone will come in.
反正東西不好還有人會進來
go ahead and fix it
再繼續把它改好
certainly
當然
That's what a lot of open source people are thinking about doing this
這是很多開放原始碼在做這方面人的想法
ok that's open source
好 那有開放原始碼
of course you just say
當然你就說
In addition to the so-called open source code I just told you
除了剛剛我跟各位講的所謂開放原始碼
Linux runs Android on it
Linux在上面跑Android
it's all open
那整個都是開放的
then everyone can share
那大家都可以分享
then i can be my phone
那我可以做我的手機
ok wait
好 等等
Of course, here is a quick summary for you.
當然這裡很快跟各位摘要一下
what phone do i have
我有什麼手機
I can develop App on it
我在上面能夠開發App
Of course there are some development environments
當然有一些開發的環境
I'll probably mention it to you guys a little bit soon.
我大概很快跟各位稍微提一下就好
Android and other development environments
Android等等開發環境
Of course, it was done in java at the beginning
當然一開始是用java來做
java is a programming language
java是一種程式語言
Later, some people made use of other development environments to do
後來有人發用其他的開發環境來做
Including C++, Python
包括C++、Python
Different open environments to do
不同的開放環境來做
There are many of these environments
那這些環境有很多
Like I just asked you to mention this one
就像我剛剛請問跟各位提到了這一個
Also includes Android Studio
還有包括Android Studio
You can develop App on it
你在上面可以開發App
Can be directly developed on Windows
可以在Windows上直接開發
then put it on and so on
然後把它裝上去等等
Well these different development environments
好 這些不同的開發環境
that many things can be done very well
那很多東西可以做得非常好
It actually has a variety of graphical interfaces
它其實各式各樣的圖形界面
you are on top
你在上面
when developing
在開發的時候呢
It can be done in a relatively simple way
可以用一個比較簡單的方式來做
OK good
OK 好
of course
那當然呢
what did you look like after you finished the program
你做完程式之後是什麼樣子
Let me tell you a little bit
跟各位稍微講一下下
OK everyone knows
OK 各位就知道
What are the things you download from Apps
你從Apps都下載下來的東西是什麼東西
It's good to feel a little bit
稍微有點感覺就好了
Normally we who write programs
一般我們寫程式的人
write my program in a programming language
用一種程式語言來寫我的程式
That in Android such a
那在Android這樣的一個
In an environment like Android
Android這樣的一個環境裡面
Everyone generally uses a language like Java
大家一般是用Java這樣的語言
for program development
來做程式的開發
What about after I develop
那我開發完之後呢
Then a program
接著會經過一個程式
We generally call it a compiler
我們一般叫做編譯器
compile it
把它編譯
After compiling
編譯完之後呢
will become another
就會變成另外一個
almost executable archive
幾乎可以執行的檔案
What about this file?
那這個檔案呢
Java has a very special concept called
Java有一個很特別的概念叫做
This BuyCode
這個BuyCode
We call it BuyCode
我們稱為BuyCode
It appeared after it was compiled
它是讓它編譯完之後出現了
The shape of this file
這個檔案的形態
It looks like something class
看起來就是什麼什麼點class
OK
OK
what's so special about this program
這個程式有什麼特別的
I want to report to you
我要跟各位報告是
This program is especially
這個程式特別在
where is it
在什麼地方呢
I used to be on a certain station
以往我在某一台
For example, the program I wrote on the X86 machine
譬如說我在X86的機器上寫完的程式
This program cannot be directly moved to
這程式不可以直接搬到
another company
另外一家公司
For example, Motorola
譬如說Motorola
The things done on the CPU run directly
做的CPU上的東西直接跑
Can't directly move to
也不能直接搬到
Run directly on the CPU of the Arm company
Arm那家公司的CPU上直接RUN
is not possible
是不可以的
Because the cross machine cannot run
因為跨的機器是不可以跑的
But where is the greatness of Jiafa?
可是加法他偉大的地方在哪裡呢
it is cross platform
它是跨平台的
Once I compile
我一旦編譯完之後
on this machine on that machine
在這個機器 在那個機器
all can run
全部都可以跑
Then why is there such a thing
那為什麼有這樣的東西呢
It's actually the concept
它其實概念是這樣
on the real machine
真正的機器上面
ran a thing called a so-called virtual machine
跑了一個東西叫做所謂的虛擬機器
above is running your program
上面在跑你的程式
Then your program is actually running on a virtual machine
那你的程式事實上是在一個虛擬機器上跑的
And this virtual machine
而這虛擬機器呢
can be placed on any machine
是可以放到任何機器上
Your program goes to the place of the virtual machine
你的程式到虛擬機器這塊地方
is safe
是安全的
can be moved at will
是可以任意移動的
So what if my program wants to run on another machine?
那如果說我的程式想跑到另外一台機器上跑怎麼辦
As long as there is a virtual machine on that machine you can run
只要那機器上有虛擬機器你就可以跑
so what to do
所以因此怎麼辦
So it means that the app I wrote is my program
因此表示說我寫的App 我這個程式
Whether it's made by Samsung
不管是三星做的
No matter it is made by HTC, it can run
不管是HTC做的 都可以跑
Because what I run out of is cross-platform
因為我跑出來的東西是跨平台的
I'm running on a virtual machine
我在虛擬機器上跑的
so you don't worry about saying
所以你就不會擔心說
What about the program on my phone?
我這個手機上的程式呢
It's Samsung's mobile phone with some apps running on it
是三星的手機上面再跑了一些App
Can I also download it on another machine
我可不可以把它同樣下載在另外一台機器上
the answer is yes
答案是可以的
Because of this so-called virtual machine concept
因為這個所謂的虛擬機器的概念
So the code is no longer bound to a certain machine
所以程式碼不再是綁定在某一台機器上
it can be tied
它是可以牽系的
OK good
OK 好
It's interesting when the concept comes out
那這個概念出現之後就很有趣
OK of course
OK 當然
Before you run this program
這個你這程式要上去跑之前
Of course you have to convert it to the Android environment
你當然要把它轉換成Android的環境
It also has a tool called DX
它還有一個工具叫DX的工具
will convert it to this
會把它轉換成這個
will do some optimization work
會做一些優化的工作
make it on your android
讓它在你的Android上面
Running performance can be better
跑起來的效能能夠比較好
OK good
OK 好
So so far, it's
那所以到這為止的話就是
At your
在你的
This is what the program running on your phone looks like
你的手機上跑的程式就是這個樣子
What do you guys download from the App Store?
那各位到 App Store 去下載的東西是長什麼樣子
You go to the App Store and if you make an app
你到 App Store 如果你做了一個程式
If you want to put it on the App Store for people to download
你想把它放在 App Store 讓人家下載的話
Basically it does one more conversion
基本上它會再做一個轉換
with another tool called AAPT
用另外一個工具叫 AAPT 的程式
After you make a package
幫你做一個包裝之後
It's called the point APK program
它就叫做點 APK 的程式
So the program you downloaded in the App Store
所以你在 App Store 下載的程式
Just click the APK program
就是點 APK 的程式
So after downloading, it will be decompressed
所以下載下來之後就會解壓說完之後
Just put it on and run
就裝上去就可以跑了
That's the basic concept
這就是基本的概念
So in this slide, I mainly want to tell you two things
所以在這張投影片我最主要跟各位講兩件事情
The first thing is on the phone
第一件是手機上的東西
The running app is cross-platform
跑的 App 是跨平台的
On this machine and that machine no matter what processor you are running
在這台機器跟那台機器不管你跑的處理器是什麼
Whether it's Motorola's
不管是 Motorola 的
It doesn't matter which one of Apple's is the same, you can run
Apple 的 哪一家都一樣都沒有關係都可以跑
Because it is running on a virtual machine
因為它是跑在一個虛擬的機器上
There is also a virtual machine on top of the entity
實體上面還有一個虛擬的機器
and only then run your program
然後才跑你的程式
OK, so the virtual machine can be implemented on different machines
OK 所以虛擬機器就可以在不同機器上都可以實做
Your layers can then be moved on top of
你的層次就可以在上面移動了
OK of course other than that
OK 當然除了這之外呢
I'm telling you
我跟各位提的是
In fact, in the end, after packaging this thing, it will be on your App Store.
其實最後還會打包完這個東西就上你的App Store
you can download
你就可以下載
Download it, unzip it, and install it
下載下來解壓說就裝上去了
OK, that layer runs on top
OK 好 那層次在上面跑
Let me tell you a few concepts
那跟各位稍微講幾個概念
What about the design of our mobile phone?
我們的手機的設計呢
It's a little bit different from your current desktop computer.
跟你現在桌上型的電腦有一點點不一樣
What about desktop computers?
在桌上型的電腦來說的話呢
if you can imagine
如果可以想像
Can I run many levels
我是不是可以跑很多支層次
It doesn't matter if your Office Powerpoint can be cut and cut
你的Office Powerpoint可以切來切去都沒有關係
But a phone isn't like your desktop computer after all.
可是手機畢竟不像你的桌上型電腦
It's just something you hold in your hand
它就是拿在手上的一支東西
It doesn't have a big screen
它螢幕也沒有很大
You seem to only do one thing at a time
你一次好像也只做一件事情
OK of course you can listen to music
OK 當然你可以邊聽音樂
Then send a message to others
然後邊跟人家送Message
OK can also be OK
OK 也可以 OK
But what about when you're looking at your phone?
不過你在關注你的手機的時候呢
Seems to be the foreground branch
似乎是前景的那一支層次
also because of this
也因為這樣子
Its design concept is a little different
它的設計概念上是有一點不太一樣的
OK
OK
First of all, let me just say a few names.
首先呢 我先講幾個名稱就好了
OK, then I'll tell you a little bit about
OK 然後跟各位稍微講一下
what its concept looks like
它的概念是什麼樣子
on the phone
在手機上面呢
What about Android phones?
Android手機上面呢
We say a thing is called activity
我們說一個東西叫做活動
called Activity
叫Activity
In fact it is used to display a screen
事實上它拿來顯示一個畫面
OK it's doing one thing
OK 它在做一件事情
it interacts with our users
它跟我們使用者互動
Except for the one thing that interacts with you
那除了跟你互動的那一個東西之外
In fact, there is something running behind
其實背後還有東西在跑
OK, for example, helping you download something
OK 譬如說在幫你下載東西
The latter thing is generally called a service
後面的東西呢 一般我們叫做是一個服務
it executes in the background
它在背景上面執行
It may be downloading from the remote end
它可能跟遠端在做下載
What about after that?
之後呢 在交給你的活動
Activity interacts with you
Activity跟你做互動
OK at the same time
OK 同時呢
You have a lot of things running together on this phone
你這支手機上有很多東西一起在跑
some material is shared
一些資料是共享的
OK, if it has to do this thing
OK 它必須要做到這件事情的話呢
It puts some data
它又把一些資料呢
do some integration
做一些整合
combined for use by other programs
組合起來給其他的程式使用
It is called Content Provider
它稱為Content Provider
There's still a lot of work going on on the phone.
那手機上還有很多工作在進行
Including saying that your battery is not very good
包括說 這個你的電量不太好
The phone will notify you that the battery is low
手機會通知你 電不夠了
what are you going to do then
那你要怎麼辦
so some notifications will appear
所以有一些通知會出現
Then if you write some programs on it
那你在上面寫一些程式的話
can also receive some responses from these systems
也可以接收這些系統發出的一些回應
And some of this requirement
還有一些這個要求
then you can do something
那你就可以做一些事情
Well, if that's the case
好 那是這樣子的話
Let's start to see how the mobile phone works
我們開始來看一下下手機怎麼動
First you open something on your phone
一開始你在手機上打開一個東西
The idea on the phone is this
在手機的想法是這樣
there is something running activity
有一個東西在跑 活動
do some processing with you in front
在前面跟你做一些處理
Then you open another thing
接著你又開一個東西
The next thing it does is put the
接著它做的動作就是把
like a stack
就像是個堆疊一樣
It puts this activity 2
它就把這活動2
Just stuff it on top of Activity 1
就塞在活動1的上面
OK so you see activity 2
OK 所以你看到是活動2
Activity 1 ran to the background below
活動1在下面跑到背景去了
What if you're driving a
如果你在開一個的時候呢
Activity 3 just run to the top
活動3就跑到上面來
so one on top of the other
所以一個疊著一個
The thing on top of it is the front neck thing
它最上面那個東西就是前頸的東西
What's underneath is called the background
底下的東西就叫背景
OK, of course you can imagine
OK 那當然各位想像
there's a front neck you face it
就有一個前頸你對著它
bottom is behind
底下都在後面
OK this is the idea of ​​the phone
OK 這是手機的想法
Because it has a small screen, do one thing at a time
因為它螢幕很小 一次做一件事情
What's on top is the foreground, what's left is the background
在上面的東西就是前景 剩下的東西叫背景
Then if you press a return key,
那你如果按一個返回鍵的時候
when jumping the top thing off
把最上面的東西跳走的時候
that thing it destroys you
那東西它就把你銷毀
Then move the back to the foreground
然後把後面的東西移到前景來
why destroy
為什麼要銷毀
In fact, this is because when mobile phones are being made
其實這是因為現在手機在製作的時候
because of its memory etc. it's small
因為它的記憶體等等這很小
Resources are limited, so it saves what it can
資源很有限 所以它能省就省
If that thing thinks you don't look at it, it will kill you
如果那東西它當作你不看就把你殺掉
But of course this is just a concept right now
不過當然這只是現在的概念
does not mean that it will continue to do so in the future
並不代表未來會繼續這樣做
But it also represents an idea of ​​the phone
不過這也代表手機的一個想法
once you look at one more thing
一次你再看一個東西
What is in front is separate from what is behind
在前面的東西跟在後面的東西是分開的
it is handled differently
它有不同的處理方式
Speaking of this, I actually tell you
講到這兒其實我跟各位
Some ways to operate the phone
把手機的一些操作的方式
I gave you some simple explanations
跟各位有做了一些簡單的一個解釋
let's see then
那我們來看一下
From then till now
從以前到現在
Android development
Android的發展
Android basically
Android基本上
There are new revisions almost every year
幾乎每年都有新的改版
No matter how it is revised
不管它怎麼改版
Everyone noticed one thing
各位都注意到一件事情
Its name is just named after dim sum
它取的名字只是用點心在取名字
Like the old one called Cupcat
就像以前的這個叫Cupcat
Until now called Marshmallow
一直到現在叫做Marshmallow
This is the October version
這是去年10月的版本
So after a while there is a version
所以過一段時間就有一個版本
all dim sum
全部都是點心
Anyway
Anyway
These versions are basically shared by mobile phones and tablets.
這些版本基本上都是手機跟平板是共用的
Except for a version like 3.0 Honeycomb
除了好像3.0 Honeycomb這一個版本之外
So this is its development
所以這個是它的發展
Everyone, the progress is actually quite fast.
各位看進展其實蠻快的
In terms of market share
那市場佔有率來看的話
Everyone, the bottom one is Marshmallow
各位這個最底下這個是Marshmallow
Because it didn't take long, right?
因為出來沒多久對不對
The more you go to the top, you will see different versions
那越往上面各位看到不同的版本
Of course, this is a lot of words to give you a feeling.
那當然各位這個很多字給各位看一個感覺而已
Aggel is the time axis
Aggel是時間軸
This Y axis is 100% all android
這Y軸是100%是所有的安卓
For example, at this point in time
譬如說米這個時間點
This time point is from the perspective of October 2013
這時間點是2013年的10月的角度去看
You can see what version is used
你就看到哪些東西是用什麼版本
what percentage
佔據多少百分比
It's normal, and you see, as time goes by,
這很正常了 各位看隨著時間的推移
A new phone will come out with a new version
就會出來新的手機用新的版本
The old ones are slowly passing by
舊的慢慢就過去了
When the new one first came out, the surplus rate was still very small.
新的剛出來的時候 佔餘率還很小
slowly grow up
慢慢慢慢就會長大
When I grow up, when time goes this way
長大的時候 時間往這邊推移的時候
This bottom marshmallow
這個最底下這個marshmallow
After a while it looks like this green
過一段時間就好像這個綠色一樣
And new ones come out, come out from under
又有新的出來 又從底下出現
will keep going like this
會這樣一直往前推
This is a state we see
這是我們看到的一個狀態
Here's a feel for some numbers for you guys
這是給各位一些數字的感覺
so far
到現在來說的話
What is the market share of Android phones?
安卓手機的話 到底市場佔餘率大概是什麼樣子
You can see that up to now, of course
各位可以看到 到現在為止當然
marshmallow is latest 6.0
marshmallow是最新的 6.0
it has 2.3%
它有2.3%
As you can see, many are still alive, right?
前面各位看到 很多還活著對不對
Of course, the mobile phone does not mean that it will be broken after a year of use.
當然手機並不是說用一年就壞掉
many things are still alive
很多東西還會活著
Look at the previous version 2.2
你看這前面2.2版
There is still 0.1% share
還有0.1%的佔有率
ok
ok
anyway
anyway
So everyone see Kickhand 4.3
所以各位看到Kickhand 4.3
What about version 4.4?
4.4這一版呢
Actually still
其實都還在
Jelly Bean is still there too
Jelly Bean也都還在
This is a very natural process
這個就是很自然而然的一個過程
it will keep pushing
它會一直往前推
Occupancy rate will make some changes
佔有率會做一些改變
good
好
then look again
那再來看
What about different smartphones?
那不同的智慧型手機呢
what is their occupancy rate like
他們的佔有率是什麼樣子
everyone see
各位看到
Android phone on top
最上面是安卓的手機
current market share
目前市場佔有率
About 82%
大概在82%左右
ok
ok
So 8 out of 10 phones are Android phones
所以10支手機有8支是安卓手機
besides that
除此之外呢
Further down is iOS
再往下是iOS
That is to say, when you see Apple's mobile phone
也就是說各位看到Apple的手機
what about share
佔有率呢
You probably see 14% now
大概各位看到現在14%
but it will float
但是它會浮動的
In 2014
在2014年的時候呢
See in 12 to 14 in 2015
看到在12到2015年是14
it keeps going up and down
它會上下不斷的浮動
What about Windows phones?
Windows的手機呢
2.8 2.5 actually
2.8 2.5其實
have been unable to rush up
一直衝不上來
About 2.3
大概就2.3
3% only
3%而已
What about Blackberry?
Blackberry呢
going from bad to worse
每況愈下
0.7、0.3
0.7、0.3
I don't know when it will disappear
不知道什麼時候就消失了
By 0.3 it has almost disappeared
到0.3已經幾乎消失了
Of course there are others
那當然還有其他呢
don't know what it is
不知道是什麼東西的
OK
OK
good
好
This is from the perspective of mobile phone distribution
這是從手機這個分佈的角度來看
then this is
那這個是
In addition, it is the report of IDC
另外是IDC的report
The front is Garden's report
前面是Garden的report
OK
OK
He also told you
他也告訴你說
The distribution is about the same
分佈大概也是差不多
everyone see
各位看到
This is XO
這是XO
Y axis is time
Y軸是時間
This is the Y axis is the market share
這是Y軸是市場佔有率
What about the top one?
那最上面這一條呢
you can imagine
各位可以想像
This is the Android phone
這就是Android的手機
OK
OK
What about the blue one?
藍色這一條呢
It is an IOS mobile phone
就是IOS的手機
OK
OK
then further down
那再往下的話
everyone see
各位看到
This is other Windows
這就是其他Windows
Bratberry, etc.
Bratberry等等
basically
基本上
The surveys conducted by the two companies are similar
兩家公司做出來的調查是差不多的
OK
OK
Both are about 82%
都是大概82%
A market distribution of left and right
左右的一個市場分佈
good
好
What about the comparison of major phones?
那主要手機的比較呢
take a quick look
很快看一下
your IOS
你的IOS的
The Phone Windows Phone Android Phone
這個手機Windows手機Android的手機
OK
OK
is their development environment etc.
是他們的開發環境等等
market share
市場佔有率
OK
OK
What about the development environment?
那開發的環境呢
from different development environments
從不同的開發環境
from java to different
從java到不同的
OK
OK
Of course one is Android
那當然一個是Android
The bottom of Android is Linux
安卓最底下是Linux
Windows phones run Windows
Windows手機跑的是Windows
What about IOS?
IOS呢
It's actually an Apple phone
它其實是Apple的手機
It actually runs the Unix operating system at the bottom
它最底層其實跑的是Unix的作業系統
OK
OK
Of course, there is Mark's operating system at the bottom
當然最底下還有Mark的作業系統
It's running BSD Unix
它在跑BSD Unix
OK
OK
Then stack it like this
然後這樣疊上來的
But you can say it belongs to Unix
不過你可以說它是屬於Unix
In this way, it is actually quite accurate.
這樣來看其實也蠻準確的
good
好
Then you say
那各位說
Is it only young people who use mobile phones?
是不是只有年輕人用手機
Actually not
其實不是的
OK
OK
Because just now many people said
因為剛剛大家很多人說
Oops, we don't know how to use mobile phones anymore
哎呀 我們不會用手機了
OK
OK
are used by young people
都是年輕人在用
Actually not
其實不是的
OK
OK
Guys you belong to this group
各位你是屬於這一群人的
Of course there are many young people here
當然還有很多年輕人在這兒
OK
OK
Then take me as an example
那就以我為例呢
look
你看
I belong to the 3 40%
我是屬於這個3 40%的人
Everyone look at this over 65 years old
各位看這個65歲以上的
8% use mobile phones and smartphones
用手機 智慧型手機有8%
20% aged 50 and over 55
50歲跟55歲以上 也有20%
If the tablet is nearly 30%
如果平板電腦 將近30%
This number may be a little more than you think.
這數字可能比你各位想像還要多一點
besides that look again
除此之外 再看一下
What is the distribution of mobile phones?
手機的分佈是什麼樣子呢
Of course, at present, Android mobile phones have 57%
當然目前來說 Android的手機是有57%
iPhone, etc.
iPhone等等
This has a different distribution
這就有不同的分佈
This is a distribution of mobile phone and age
這個是手機跟年齡的一個分佈
So we're not really special
所以其實我們並不是很特別的
In fact, each of us occupies a large proportion in it.
我們每一個人其實在裡面佔據的比例都很大的
What about the mobile phone?
各位說那手機呢
Is it just that of course we just say
是不是只有 當然我們就說
So many people use mobile phones
那手機這東西那麼多人在上面使用
what was the year like
那年著度是什麼樣子
Are we Taiwanese particularly aged?
我們台灣人是不是年著度特別高
Actually not OK
其實不是的 OK
Someone is worse than us OK
有人比我們還慘 OK
let's take a look
我們來看一看
If you see the green part above, it is a TV
上面各位看到綠色的部分的話是電視
So you said Indonesians like to watch TV
所以你說印尼人喜歡看電視
Thai people see less
泰國人看的比較少一點
The blue part is your personal computer and your PC
藍色的部分是你的個人電腦跟你的PC
The yellow part is the mobile phone
這個黃色的部分是手機
behind the tablet
後面是平板
everyone see
各位看到
If you look at it from this point of view
如果從這角度來看的話
you will see some very interesting fact
你會看到一些很有趣的一個事實
The distribution of people in different places is actually very different
不同地方的人的分布其實很不一樣
Of course, you are most concerned about what about us.
當然各位最關心說那我們怎麼樣
take a look everyone
各位看一下
Actually we are miserable
其實我們蠻慘的
This one still looks like a blue TV
這一條還是像藍色的電視
red is your pc
紅色是你的個人電腦
The green one is the phone
綠色的是手機
blue is
藍色的才是
sorry the purple one is your tablet
對不起紫色的才是你的平板電腦
everyone see
各位看到
The use of so many screens above
這麼多螢幕的使用上面
Our phone is the highest 197
我們的手機是最高的197
actually amazing
其實很驚人的
So if you look at it this way
所以這樣來看的話
Actually we beat almost everyone
其實我們打敗了幾乎所有人
right
對不對
Since the Japanese are not our opponents, right?
從日本人不是我們對手對不對
Indonesians are nothing to look at, right?
印尼人也沒什麼好看的對不對
Okay, so we look pretty good.
好 所以我們看起來還蠻厲害的
OK
OK
Taiwanese people are really sticky to their phones
台灣人真的很黏手機
OK good
OK 好
Then we are all glued to our phones, OK
那我們都很黏手機 OK
Actually we all know that OK
這其實我們大家都知道 OK
Then why am I so clingy to my phone?
那為什麼我會這麼黏手機
because it can do many things
因為它可以做很多事情
So so let's take a look
所以因此我們來看一看
Why is this called a smartphone?
這個為什麼叫智慧型手機
So why is it called a smartphone?
那其實它為什麼叫智慧型手機
Actually there's something behind it
其實它背後有什麼東西
So that's why I use this phone
所以因此我才會用這個手機
Because you're not using it to make calls
因為你不是拿它來打電話而已
Use it to do many things OK
拿來做很多事情 OK
what things
哪些事情呢
For example, the services behind you may include
譬如說你背後的服務可能有包括
Management of your personal information
你個人資訊的管理
For example, your blog
譬如說你的部落格
your carrant
你的carrant
all your forms
你的所有的形式
You are like me, everything is online OK
你像我所有的東西全部都上網 OK
when you often go outside
你常常到外面走的時候
you will check
你會查查看
Is there any good food nearby? OK
這附近有沒有好吃的 OK
You will do some location based services
你會做一些location based的服務
location-based services
跟位置有關的服務
then you may do many other
那你可能會做很多其他
For example, all my information is uploaded to the so-called
譬如說我的資料全部上到所謂的
Go to Jobbox
Jobbox上面去
I can download it on every machine
我在每一台機器都可以下載
OK
OK
so you have some
所以你有一些
some so-called general services
一些所謂的一般性的服務
Of course there are many others
當然還有很多其他的
Let's say you share a photo on
譬如說你在上面分享照片
or you read some news on it
或是你在上面看一些新聞
so you'll notice
所以你會注意到
There's actually a lot of stuff you do on it
其實有很多東西你在上面做的
like a blog
像部落格
Many people read blogs
很多人看部落格的
OK
OK
Many people spend a lot of time on it every day
每天很多人在上面花了很多時間
your form
你的形式力
maybe you're not alone
可能不是你一個人看
You watch alone with many people
你一個人跟很多人一起看
For example, say your colleagues are doing something together
譬如說你的同事一起在做一些事情
Everyone wants to know if you are busy now
大家想知道說你現在有沒有很忙
He doesn't need to call you
他不用打電話問你
He went directly to Google to see
他直接上Google看
you just share it
你只要分享出去就行了
And of course you guys just looked at your map.
還有當然各位剛看過了你的地圖
OK
OK
you can find a lot of things on it
你在上面可以找很多東西
Your hard drive can be placed in the cloud
你的硬碟可以放在雲端
everyone can go up and see
大家都可以上去看
You can go up and use it on every machine
你在每一台機器都可以上去使用
OK
OK
And you read the news
還有你的看了這些新聞
or you can share
或是你可以分享
like your photo etc.
像你的照片等等
Then why do this thing
那為什麼可以做這件事情
There must be something behind it to support these services
一定背後有一些東西來支撐這些服務
Otherwise how can we get so many things
要不然我們怎麼能夠得到這麼多東西
you can imagine
各位可以想像
So many people put videos on their computers
這麼多人都把影片放到電腦上面去了
Where did you put it?
到底放到哪兒去了
We all know that we have gone to the cloud
大家都知道到雲端上面去了
There's a really huge machine over there in the back
後面有一個非常巨大的機器在那邊
it can hold almost unlimited amount of stuff
它可以放幾乎無限多的東西
you want to check anything
你要查任何東西
When you hit Google to ingest something
你打Google去攝取一個東西的時候
It's far away and I don't know where it is
它就在很遠的地方不知道在哪邊
After collecting the items for you, they will be delivered to you.
幫你收取完東西就送到你面前了
so what does it mean
所以表示什麼
Indicates that there should be a very huge machine behind it
表示背後應該有一個非常巨大的一台機器
or a bunch of machines
或是一群機器
in support of all your services
在支撐你的所有的服務
To provide the blog you just saw
來提供你剛剛看到的部落格也好
your facebook too
你的Facebook也好
to do all these things
來做這些所有的事情
So there must be a very powerful machine behind it
所以背後一定要有一個非常厲害的機器
it provides you with all these services
它提供給你這些所有的服務
OK
OK
Everyone knows that is more beautiful
那更漂亮的各位都知道
people on facebook now
現在Facebook上去的人
actually very very amazing
其實非常非常驚人
This is from 2012 to 2014
這是從2012年一直到2014年
You see it keeps increasing every year
你看每年一直在增加
has been increasing
一直在增加
That number is millions
那這個數字是百萬的
Then you see
那各位看到
This 1393 million
這個1393百萬
what is that
那就是什麼
million trillion billion billion
百萬千萬億十億
OK there are 1.3 billion people
OK 有13億人
nearly 1.4 billion people
將近14億人
Also use Facebook on the Internet
同時在網路上面用Facebook
OK so 1.4 billion people
OK 所以14億的人
directly on top
直接一起在上面一起用
mean what
表示什麼
It must continue to be able to carry this matter
它後面必須要繼續能夠承載這件事情
And what?
而且呢
From 2012 until 2014
從2012年一直到2014年
Until you find out all the way down
到一直往下各位發現
it will continue to grow
它會繼續往下成長
Because the world's population is billions of people
因為全世界的人口有幾十億人
OK it will continue to grow
OK 它會再繼續長
What about the service behind it?
它背後的這個服務呢
have to be able to keep supporting it
必須要能夠繼續支撐它
OK what does that mean
OK 那表示什麼
It must have a huge ecosystem behind it
它一定有一個巨大的生態系在後面
to push all this stuff
來推動這所有的東西
OK
OK
so that our phone
所以這樣才能讓我們的手機
get all the services we want
得到我們所有想要的服務
OK, so when you look at it from this angle
OK 所以從這角度來看的時候呢
then let's see
那我們就來看看說
what are these things
這些東西是什麼
what is
是什麼
Actually
其實呢
What about the things behind this huge service?
後面支撐這個巨大服務的東西呢
Cloud Computing
就是各位都知道的雲端計算
ok you have a huge cloud platform over there
ok 你有個巨大的雲端平台在哪邊
Because why is it called cloud
因為為什麼叫雲端
you don't know where you are, do you?
你也不知道在哪裡對不對
Is it right to face in the cloud anyway?
反正在雲裡面對不對
I can't see it's there
我也看不到就在那裡
I can use what I want
我要用的我就可以用
ok good
ok 好
So let's define what is cloud computing
那所以我們來定義什麼叫雲端計算
What about cloud computing from an engineering perspective?
雲端計算用工程的角度來看的話呢
It basically provides a bunch of machines
它基本上提供了一堆機器
The machine is not necessarily physical
機器不見得是實體的喔
it is virtual
它是虛擬的
Behind is thousands of machines on it
後面就是成千上萬的機器在上面
It supports all the services on it
它在上面支撐了所有的服務
ok, let’s run this thing on a real machine
ok 那在真正的機器上來跑這個東西
ok, the machines will continue to increase
ok 那機器會不斷的增加
ok, let's look at it from an engineering point of view
ok 好 我們從工程的角度來看
What about from a business point of view?
那如果從商業的角度來看呢
basically it's a thing
基本上它就是一個東西
there's a way there's a service for me
有一個方法 有一個服務給我
it keeps growing
它不斷會成長
ok
ok
And it's always there
而且呢 它隨時都在
It can support very large applications
非常大型的應用 他也能夠支撐得住
Of course, what are the characteristics of cloud computing?
那當然表示 雲端計算有什麼特性呢
The first his platform is virtual
第一個 他的平台是虛擬的
Where is it, you don't really care
在哪邊 其實你並不在意的
Maybe in Taiwan Maybe in Europe Maybe in America
可能在台灣 可能在歐洲 可能在美國
You don't mind too much, it's over there anyway.
你也不是很介意 反正就在那邊
OK, what about the second one?
OK 第二個呢
Everything has to be able to continue to grow
所有東西必須要能夠繼續成長的
I want to be able to support a billion people now
我要能夠支持現在十億人
In the future, this set of tools must be able to support two billion people
未來這套東西要能夠支持二十億人
Three billion people must continue to rise
三十億人 必須往上繼續漲
All his services must be efficient
他的所有服務必須要很有效率的
unable to follow the process of growing up
不能夠跟著成長的過程中
when I click Google to do an ingest
我按一下Google做一個攝取的時候
Come back in ten minutes, no
十分鐘才回來 不行的
OK press it and you will be back immediately
OK 按了立刻就要回來
OK for all service types
OK 所有的服務型態
actually becomes very elastic
其實會變得非常有彈性的
when the clouds appear
那雲端出現的時候
what is the impact on us
對我們的衝擊是什麼
Of course the first
當然第一個
you'll find that says where do you put the pictures
你會發現說 你在哪裡放照片
Well, it's in my computer.
好然在放在自己的電腦裡面嘛
Of course there are problems
當然有問題
I also let it go OK
我也有放啦 OK
it's nothing to be ashamed of
這沒有什麼好丟臉的
But where are many people
可是很多人放在哪
I don’t know where it’s right, in the cloud, right?
不知道哪裡對不對 在雲端對不對
everyone can see
大家都可以看
Your usage behavior is starting to change
你的使用行為開始在改變了
Behavior Change
其實不只使用行為改變
All manufacturers are also greatly affected
所有的廠商也受到巨大的影響
I can give you an example
我可以各位舉一個例子
Everyone see what is the most profitable for Microsoft
各位看到 Microsoft 最賺錢是什麼
What is Microsoft's most profitable
微軟最賺錢是什麼
It's not that Windows is the most profitable Office
其實不是 Windows 是 Office 最賺錢的
OK
OK
It's Word's Powerpoint that makes the most money with these things
它的 Word 的 Powerpoint 最賺錢這些東西
But Microsoft is getting scared too
可是微軟也開始害怕了
Why
為什麼
because before
因為以前呢
Before, you were using Word and Powerpoint
以前呢 你在使用 Word 跟 Powerpoint
Do you remember
各位記不記得
You're all done editing on this one machine and it's here
你都在這一台機器上做完編輯 就存在這裡
What do you want to do when another machine is used
你想在另外一台機器用的時候 你做什麼事
copy him out
是把他拷貝出來
Get another machine and store it in
拿到另外一台機器 再把它存進去
Everyone recently, everyone uses Office
各位最近 各位用 Office
did you find one thing
有沒有發現一件事情
You can log in with an account
你可以登錄一個帳號
After you change it, it can exist on it
你把它改完之後就可以存在上面
no idea where it is
不知道在哪裡
If you log in on another machine, you can watch it directly
你在另外一台機器如果登錄就可以直接看了
So it's clouded
所以其實雲端化了
things have gone up
東西已經上去了
Why
為什麼
Because it actually faces the challenge of the cloud
因為它其實面臨到雲端的挑戰
so therefore
所以因此呢
Include it app started changing
包括它應用程式開始改變了
It is no longer a stand-alone program
它不再是單機板的程式
Start is a cross-machine program
開始是跨機器的程式
Its service also does not allow you to modify the program on a machine
它的服務也不在一台機器上讓你修改程式
Started going out across machines
開始跨機器出去了
So this time you will find
所以這個時候你就會發現
office has entered its life and death challenge
office已經開始進入它的生死存亡的挑戰了
Because includes OpenOffice
因為包括OpenOffice
Everyone including Google wants to do this business
包括Google大家都想做這個生意
It's so easy to make money, it has to make money
這麼好賺錢它也要賺
Once everything is online
所有東西一旦上了網之後呢
After no longer the same machine
不再同一台機器之後呢
Your previous advantage may become your biggest obstacle now
你以前的優勢可能就變成你現在最大的阻礙了
everyone has to go up
大家都要上去
So the nature of apps starts to change
所以應用程式的本質開始改變了
Everything starts to go to the cloud
所有東西開始雲端化全部上去了
ok
ok
What about after going up?
一上去之後呢
How to use it on your mobile device
你的行動裝置上的使用方式
It also begins to discover connections with the way you use it on your desk
跟你桌上的使用方式也開始發現連結了
OK
OK
everyone pay attention
各位注意注意到
Recently, if you have used this Apple mobile phone
最近你如果有使用這個 Apple 的這個手機
you also noticed one thing
你也注意到一件事情
your call to your cell phone
你的電話打到你的手機
Because your tablet can also call, right?
因為你平板也會叫 對不對
Why
為什麼
Because it actually starts to connect
因為其實開始串聯了
start to link together
開始連結在一起了
This is an example to tell you
這就是一個例子告訴各位呢
In fact your application
其實你的應用程式
No longer a stand-alone application
不再是單機化的應用程式
Start the network cloud thing
開始網路雲端化的東西
start walking in that direction
開始往那方向走
The concept of desktop software
所謂桌上型軟體的概念
Further down the time has begun to cease to exist
再往下的時間已經開始不復存在了
What started out as a decentralized web
開始變成是分散式化網路的東西
OK
OK
that's why
這也是為什麼呢
In fact, Microsoft now
其實微軟現在呢
So hard to make a push to the cloud part
這麼努力的往雲端這部分來做一個推進
because
因為呢
the world has begun to change
世界已經開始改變了
It's not what it used to be
不再是過去的樣子了
of course
那當然呢
It also provides us with great opportunities
它也提供給我們巨大的機會啊
OK
OK
It's like I'm telling you
那就像我跟各位講
What about cloud computing?
雲端計算呢
it has to be successful
它這東西要能夠成功
Of course there are several prerequisites
當然有幾個先決條件
Guys, what about after you put your photos in the cloud?
各位 你把你的照片放到雲端之後呢
you have to show others
你要給別人看
you say sorry
你說對不起啊
I can't see it OK
看不到了 OK
I don't know why OK
不知道為什麼 OK
you are very very depressed
你非常非常沮喪
because one thing is put in one place
因為一個東西放到一個地方
you should always have it
你要隨時可以取得
availability is very important
availability非常重要
Anytime I can use it I can see OK
隨時我可以要用 我就可以看到 OK
not only that
不只是這樣
After I put things in the cloud
我東西放到雲端之後
I'm worried about being stolen, right?
我擔心被人家偷走了對不對
i have some pictures
我有些照片
I have some information that was blocked by my test paper
我有些資料 被我的考卷
I am already very happy when I go to the cloud student
我上到雲端學生已經很開心
if he can download
如果他可以下載的話
He has an exam tomorrow, right?
他明天就會考試了對不對
so no
所以不行啊
I must lock it up OK
我一定要把它鎖起來 OK
My storage space will continue to grow OK
我的儲存空間要不斷的長大 OK
can handle a billion people today
今天可以應付十億人
Can handle two billion people in the future
以後可以應付二十億人
Facebook will say
Facebook會說
Sorry, I only serve you 1.3 billion people today
對不起啊 我今天只服務你們十三億人
Sorry for the new person, I won't accept it OK
新的人來對不起我不收了 OK
no way right
不會嘛 對不對
He said try his best, try his best
他說盡量上 盡量上
I can do two billion, three billion, I'm fine, right?
我還可以二十億 三十億我也沒問題對不對
so he doesn't move
所以他要不動
Countable growth
算的成長
OK
OK
rapid growth
快速的成長
Not only you are storing and computing
不只你是儲存計算
all things grow
所有東西都要成長
Then what
然後呢
After everything is online
所有東西上了網路之後
you guys noticed one thing
各位注意到一件事情
If you are in the company
你如果有在公司裡面
or you are in school
或是你在學校裡面
did you notice one thing
你有沒有注意到一件事情
Many things are no longer available
很多東西已經不買了
OK
OK
for example
舉個例子來說
in my lab
我的實驗室裡面呢
I've stopped buying some servers
我已經不再買一些伺服器了
I rented it
我用租的
OK
OK
all online
全部上網
machine broken
機器壞掉
I hold him accountable
我找他負責
OK
OK
Everything is on the Internet
所有東西都上到網路上去了
so my students
所以我的學生
or assistant
或者說助理
To download any file
要下載任何檔案
I said go there and download it
我說去那邊下載就好了
24 hours shop
24小時開店
OK
OK
guaranteed to get
保證拿得到
die and find him responsible
死掉找他負責
right
對不對
Look everyone
各位看啊
He has a license with me
他跟我有一個license
he rented me this thing
他租給我這個東西
He guarantees me 24 hours
他保證我24小時
365 days a day
一天365天
Every second must be able to walk
紛紛秒秒都要能夠walk
and fast
而且速度要很快
or he pays me
要不然他賠我錢
OK
OK
So actually notice that something is starting to change
所以其實注意到一些東西開始在改變
Some hardware items are not available for purchase
硬體有些東西不買了
I use pig software, can I still buy it?
我用豬的 軟體還買不買
Of course you don't buy some software
當然有些軟體你也不買
Because there are no more machines, right?
因為連機器都沒有了對不對
I may just use that machine to type directly on it
我可能就是用那個機器在上面直接打東西
It's fine to pay as long as it takes to sleep.
打打臥的 用多久付多久錢就好了
So things will change, right?
所以東西就會變了對不對
So the new economic order of all things has gradually arrived
所以所有東西新的經濟秩序已經逐漸會到來
Because many things I no longer need to acquire
因為很多東西我不再需要獲得
some things i bring with pigs
有些東西我用豬帶的
I'm a pig machine, I'm a pig software
我豬機器 我豬軟體
I don't want it
我不想要就不要
I opened a shop, why do I buy so many machines
我開店了 我幹嘛買那麼多機器
I just talk to anyone, whether it's Amazon
我只要去跟任何家 不管是Amazon
Whether it is Chunghwa Telecom, rent this computer room
不管是中華電信 租個這個機房
Just go straight up and open the shop
東西就直接上去 就開店了
If you want to expand today, just rent a few more machines
那今天想擴張 也就多租幾台機器嘛
got bigger
就變大了
So you can grow up and get smaller at any time
所以隨時可以長大可以變小
also sell us
還賣給我們
So a lot of things started to change
所以因此很多東西就開始變了
I buy a software, I don't have to think about it for a long time
我買一個軟體我不用想了半天
I rent it for two days and use it. I don’t like returning it to him.
我租兩天用用看 不喜歡退給他
Of course, many things have changed by then.
當然這時候很多東西就跟著改變了
In fact, the cloud drives a lot of services behind it.
雲端其實它背後推動了非常多的服務
Cause our mobile phone has a lot of power
造成我們手機有很大很大的力量
Support turning into a smart phone
支持變成一個智慧型的手機
But it is actually changing our whole world
可是它其實也正在改變我們整個世界
not just like that
不只是這樣子
let's go on
我們再繼續來看
What is cloud computing
什麼是雲端計算
When it comes to this, everyone will say
講到這兒 大家就說
Cloud computing is in the very deep cloud
雲端計算就是在很深很深的雲裡面
something is running
有一些東西在跑
I can save things, I can run data
我可以存東西 我可以跑資料
I just ask for what I want
我想要什麼就跟它要就好了
it does look like this
的確像是這樣子
Since there is a cloud, my things can exist on it
既然有一個雲端 我東西可以存在上面
Tell me, where is this cloud?
各位就說 這個雲在哪邊呢
it may not matter to you
對你來說可能不是很在乎
but some people care
可是對有些人在乎的
For example, they care about hospitals and the government.
譬如說對醫院 對政府是在乎的
He said
他說
There is a cloud today and I put things on it
今天有個雲 我東西放在上面
Many of my important health insurance information, if I put them there
我的很多重要健保資料 我如果都放在那裡
Today, the United States treats it as a leak.
今天呢 後面美國通通把它當漏走了
OK, it doesn't seem to work, right?
OK 好像不太行吧 對不對
or individuals, everyone's personally identifiable information has been downloaded
或個人 大家的個人身份資料都被下載走了
no way, right?
也不行 對不對
So at this time, a lot of ideas came out, including what
所以這時候就出現很多想法出來 包括什麼
What about clouds? Some are public clouds.
雲呢 有些是屬於公用的雲
some are proprietary some are hybrid
有些是私有的 有些是混合型的
The government may say that I want to build a cloud
政府可能就說我要做一個雲
This cloud is used by all government units and is private
這個雲是所有給政府單位一起來用的 是private的
Then this Chinese Academy may also have a cloud
那這個中文院可能也有一個雲
OK then we have some things that might be more rentable
OK 那我們有些東西可能更加租的
We probably only use Google and the public cloud
我們大概只用Google 還有公用的雲
You can do a lot of things on it
大家在上面可以做很多事情
After cloud computing, as I just mentioned
有雲端計算之後呢 就像我剛剛各位提到
It supports a huge application that provides the use of our mobile phones
它支撐了巨大的運用 提供我們手機的使用
But at the same time, let's look at it again, since there is a cloud
可是同時呢 我們再來看 既然有雲端之後呢
There are a few well-known nouns, let me explain to you a little
有幾個很有名的名詞 我跟各位稍微解釋一下
OK like what?
OK 像哪些東西呢
Some of you have heard of cloud computing, you may have heard of the so-called
各位有些聽過雲端運算 可能聽過所謂的
So software-level services, the so-called SARS
所以軟體級服務 所謂的SARS
Platform-level services and so-called
平台級服務 還有所謂的
This infrastructure may be an architecture-level service
這個infrastructure 可能是架構級服務
So what is software-level service?
那什麼叫軟體級服務呢
Running this software is basically a service
跑這個軟體基本上就是一個服務
like you use Gmail
就像各位用Gmail
that is a software
那就是一個軟體
where is this software running
這軟體在哪跑
You don't really care, do you?
你也不是很在意對不對
Any machine can run
任何來機器都可以跑
Anyway, as long as you connect it, you can use it.
反正只要連上去就可以用
Well, platform-level services
好 那平台級服務
like these things
像這些東西呢
Just like the business Microsoft does
就像Microsoft做的生意就這一個
it runs a platform on it
它在上面跑一個平台
Everyone has heard of Azoo
各位都聽過叫Azoo
There are many development tools on it
它上面可以很多開發工具
So you don't have to rent a platform
所以你也不用去租平台
There is no need to buy a database from him
也不用跟它買data base
you just rent that thing for it
你就給它租那東西
You can develop things on it
在上面就可以開發東西
you can do business
就可以做生意了
Or like Amazon does this business
或是說像Amazon就做這個生意
it provides these machines
它提供這些機器
you can rent some machines for it
你可以給它租幾台機器
you can put things on it
在上面你就可以裝東西
Let me give you another example
我再給各位舉一個例子
How many of you have heard of box grabbing?
各位有沒有多少人聽過抓box
What is Jobbox? Everyone, is it a piece of software?
Jobbox是什麼呢? 各位它是不是一個軟體
After I installed this software
這個軟體我把它裝起來之後
I can move between several computers
我可以在好幾台電腦之間
share some files, right?
共享一些檔案對不對
After all installed, it will automatically
都裝起來之後它自動
Change it here and help me sync
這裡改它又幫我sync
Change it here and copy it for me
這裡改它又幫我copy過來
It helps me keep both sides the same
它幫我維持兩邊是一樣的
Then I tell Jobbox
那我跟Jobbox說
I will buy 100GB from you a year
我一年跟你買100GB
OK 100 GIGA such a space
OK 100個GIGA這樣的一個空間
Does Amazon actually have its own machines?
其實Amazon自己有機器嗎?
Sorry, does Jobbox have machines?
對不起Jobbox是有機器嗎?
Jobbox without machine
Jobbox沒有機器的
Jobbox is rented from Amazon
Jobbox是跟Amazon租的
OK Amazon offers a lot of machines
OK Amazon提供了很多機器
what about these machines
那這些機器呢
How much CPU and how much storage space?
多少CPU啊多少儲存空間啊
Just rent from Jobbox
Jobbox就跟它租
Then Jobbox will be the second landlord
那Jobbox做二房東
Jobbox provides software services
Jobbox提供軟體服務
Then I rent with Jobbox
那我跟Jobbox租
I want to buy 100GB OK with it
我要跟它買100GB OK
then i pay for it
然後我付它錢
What about after Jobbox collects a lot of money?
那Jobbox收了很多錢之後呢
Rent things from Amazon for cheaper
用更便宜的錢去跟Amazon租東西
So Jobbox
所以Jobbox
second landlord
二房東
He is software service
他是software service
Amazon provides the machine
Amazon提供機器
he is the real landlord
他是真正的房東
So everyone makes their own money layer by layer
所以一層一層大家賺各自的錢
This is from the point of view of cloud computing
這是從雲端計算的角度來看
Cloud computing is actually a huge ecosystem
雲端計算其實是一個巨大的生態系
can think about it
可以想想看
Some people rent machines and sell machines
有一些人是租機器 賣機器的
Just like we have a lot of people selling machines in Taiwan
就像我們台灣有很多人賣機器
Give these Google stores these companies
給這些Google店這些公司
Someone is manipulating the environment
有人操縱這個環境
Companies like Google and Amazon
像Google這些Amazon這些公司
Let's continue to stack things on top of each other.
大家在上面再繼續一層一層疊的東西起來
So at the bottom there is provided
所以最底下有提供
The whole cloud structure thing
整個雲端的結構的東西
Someone provides the platform, someone provides the software
有人提供平台 有人提供軟體
Someone provided the so-called solution
有人提供所謂的解決方案
he tells people what to do
他告訴人家怎麼做事
How to build a system
怎麼建一台系統起來
So it's actually a huge ecosystem inside.
所以它其實是一個巨大的生態系在裡面
supports the entire so-called cloud computing
支撐了整個所謂的雲端計算
What do you think is the difference between cloud computing and data storage in the past?
各位說雲端計算跟過去的資料儲存有什麼不一樣
very different
很不一樣
So you used to have a data center in this place
所以你以前有個資料中心在這個地方
Then I have information, I'm afraid I won't see it
那我有資料呢 我怕不見
So I use another MIRROR over there
所以我再用一個MIRROR在那邊
which side copy
哪邊copy
copy to copy to
copy來copy去
For fear of data loss
因為怕資料掉了
Think about it, everyone in the cloud
雲端各位想想看
Is a huge data center that can grow
是一個可以成長的巨大的資料中心
it will keep growing by itself
它自己就會一直成長
and it does all the backups by itself
而且它自己做所有的備份
do all the management
做所有的管理
You don't have to worry about these things anymore
你不用再去管這些東西了
ok of course
好 那當然呢
In fact, how to use these services in this cloud
其實怎麼去使用這個雲端的這些服務
Everyone is using it, right?
各位都在用了對不對
like you use your phone
就像你用你的手機
your smartphone
你的智慧型手機
It's good to run all your blogs on it
在上面跑你的所有的部落格也好
run your facebook
跑你的facebook臉書
In fact, they are using the service behind
其實都在用背後的服務
so what is facebook
所以臉書是什麼
Facebook is the Service
臉書就是這個Service
Suffer as a Service
Suffer as a Service
software as a service
軟體即是服務
So Facebook is like Gmail
所以臉書就像Gmail一樣
it offers you a service
它提供給你一個服務
through this thing
透過這個東西
You can get a lot of information
你可以取得很多很多資料
can do with everyone
跟大家可以做
an interaction in this community
這個社群的一個互動
Of course, there are many other things besides mobile phones.
當然手機之外呢還有很多
Including everyone who sees your personal computer
包括各位看到你的個人電腦
or even on the tv
或甚至在電視上面
Now it is becoming more and more popular
現在逐漸越來越普及了
OK you can do an access to cloud data
OK 你可以做雲端資料的一個存取
OK, of course the platform has many possibilities
OK 好 當然平台有很多可能性
You may be Windows, you may be Android
你可能是Windows 可能是Android
Of course you could be Apple
當然你有可能是Apple
OK, well, there are actually many things behind it.
OK 好 那其實背後還有很多東西在裡面
just like you mentioned
就像剛剛各位提到
We have a huge machine behind the cloud
我們在雲端後面有一個巨大的機器
run a lot of software on it
在上面跑很多很多軟體
They are available from my phone
透過我的手機可以使用它們
OK good
OK 好
What about during this use?
那在這個使用過程中呢
you probably do a lot of different things
你可能做了很多不同的東西
Let's say you're doing a search for something
譬如說你在做一些東西的搜尋
For example, if you Google, who is Guo Dawei?
譬如說你Google 郭大偉是誰
ok ok of course
OK 好 那當然
when you often ask some questions
你常常在問一些問題的時候
you will find that say
你會發現說
Your stuff seems to be getting smarter
你的東西好像變聰明了
OK even
OK 甚至呢
you guys noticed something
各位注意到一些事情
Many of you use Gmail
各位很多人用Gmail
Then if you go to buy a plane ticket
那你如果去買機票
when your
當你的
When the confirmation letter of this ticket is sent to you sometimes
這個機票有時候確認信寄給你的時候呢
you will find one thing
你會發現到一件事情
when you look at your this one day
當你有天在看你的這個
when you form d
你的形式d的時候
You will find that it automatically added for you
你會發現它自動幫你加了
ok then you will be scared
ok 那你會很害怕
Why did you add something, right?
怎麼會加了東西對不對
mean what
表示什麼
For example, someone is peeking at your email, right?
比如說有人在偷看你的email對不對
That is to say, when this thing is being transmitted
也就是說在這個東西在傳送的時候
Some of this system and software are already learning
有些這個系統跟軟體已經在學習了
Include it less than your email when sending
包括它少過你的email在傳送的時候
Or when stored on its gmail platform
或儲存在它gmail的平台上的時候呢
it's actually less
它其實已經少過了
it knows something
它知道一些東西了
it knows a lot about you
它知道很多很多你的事情
then of course you should be afraid
那你當然應該害怕
computer seems smart
電腦好像很聰明
it knows many things about me
它知道我很多事情
How does it know so many things about me?
它怎麼會知道我很多事情呢
There must be a great artificial intelligence behind it
必然後面有一個很偉大的人工智慧在後面
So it will learn the above material
所以它會學習上面的資料
it will draw some conclusions
它會得到一些結論
Provide you with the so-called best service
提供給你所謂最好的服務
But it also knows you best
可它也最了解你
sounds scary
聽起來蠻可怕的
The computer starts to learn from a large amount of data
那電腦從大量的資料裡面開始學習著
these things
這些東西
so he can make some judgments
因此他可以做一些判斷
He offers you what he thinks is the best service
他提供給你他認為最好的服務
Of course he makes the most money from you
當然從你身上賺他最多的錢
what is machine learning
那機器學習是什麼
What about machine learning?
機器學習呢
basically a science
基本上就是一種科學
He learns from a large amount of information
他從大量的資料裡面去做學習
Let's say you lose some rules to him
譬如說你輸給他一些規則
he can judge
他就可以判斷說
because you're dizzy
因為你頭昏腦脹
so you can't speak
所以你講不出話
He said you might have had a stroke or you might have a cold
他說你可能中風或是你感冒
or many ways of learning
或是很多種學習方式
Not just the learning of the so-called rules
不只是所謂的規則的學習
even so-called directed learning
甚至所謂的指導式的學習
you give him some strength
你給他一些實力
He just makes some distinctions
他就做一些分辨
and then do some classification
然後做一些分類
Then he starts to study
然後他就開始學習
know something
知道什麼一些東西
Or give him information and he will start to distinguish
或是給他資料他就開始分辨
Or say you give him some cases
或是說你給他一些案例
he learned
他就學習了
so there are different techniques
所以有不同的技術
doing so-called machine learning
在做所謂的機器學習
From this information he can gain new knowledge
從這資料他能夠得到新的知識
so he can make some judgments
因此他就可以做一些判斷
He also knows what to look for
他也知道要去搜尋什麼東西
Well, of course, in this day and age
那當然 現在這個時代呢
In fact, because of the entire cloud technology
其實也因為整個雲端的技術
Also due to the generation of large amounts of data
也因為大量資料的產生
We use above
我們在上面使用
So another huge opportunity arose
因此又有一個巨大的機會出現
It's not just cloud computing that's a huge opportunity
不是只有雲端計算是一個巨大的機會
OK phone?
OK 手機呢
Cloud computing is a huge opportunity
雲端計算都是巨大的機會
This whole thing keeps going
這整個東西一直走下去
In fact, there is another huge opportunity
其實又產生一個巨大的機會
data science
就所謂的資料科學
When you have so much data on it
當你有這麼多資料在上面的時候呢
if you study it hard
你如果好好去學習它
you will learn a lot
你就會學會很多東西
OK, what about the amount of data?
OK 資料量呢
grow very, very energetic
成長得非常非常精能
everybody knows
大家都知道
OK various information
OK 各式各樣的資料
There are many types
種類非常的多
OK, some information is right and wrong
OK 有些資料對的跟不對的
you don't know
你也不知道
Some might be fake anyway
反正有些可能是假的
some really are in there anyway
有些真的 反正都在那裡面
OK so much information
OK 有這麼多資料
In fact, you start analyzing
其實你就開始分析
can start learning
可以開始學習
can do many things
可以做很多事情
e.g. e-commerce
譬如說電子商務
After a period of time
過一段時間
He knows what Guo Dawei likes to buy
他就知道郭大維喜歡買什麼
OK at night
OK 晚上的時候
what should he sell
應該賣他什麼東西
OK that
OK 那
When is the time to sell him what?
什麼時候到了應該賣給他什麼
Because of his family, which of his family members might buy those things?
因為他家 他有哪些家人可能會買那些東西
He tried to sell you
他想辦法賣給你
The same goes for medical care, with so many case files
醫療也是一樣 有這麼多病例資料
he started to analyze
他就開始分析
He said that Asians may be more prone to some diseases
他說亞洲人可能比較容易得什麼病
What might happen if you take some medicine
如果吃了什麼藥 可能會怎麼樣
So a lot of stuff started coming out
所以很多東西開始出來了
when manufacturing
生產製造的時候
I thought I had so many production materials
我以為我這麼多生產資料
I can do analysis
我就可以做分析了
For example, I can learn from many processes
譬如說我就可以從很多製程上
something went wrong i can do image processing
發生一些問題 我可以做影像處理
See if there are any flaws in the things that are said to be made
看看說做出來的東西有沒有一些瑕疵
I can see without human eyes
我就可以不用人眼再看
It will be scanned automatically after a while
過一段時間就自動掃描出來
this thing may be broken
就這東西可能壞掉了
Then you come to make further judgments
那你再來做進一步的判定
social network life science
社群網路生命科學
So new big opportunities start to appear
因此新的巨大的機會就開始出現了
Of course this is nothing
當然這東西都比不上什麼
Nothing compares to the fact that through all the computers
都比不上其實透過所有的電腦
through all internet
透過所有的網際網路
Through all these apps and your phone
透過所有的這些軟體跟你的手機
We're actually creating a gigantic machine
其實我們在創造一個巨大的機器
OK this huge machine is
OK 這個巨大的機器就是
Including you and me we form a huge machine
包括你跟我我們組成一個巨大的機器
What do you do when you don't know many things
各位很多事情你不知道的時候 你幹什麼
Go online and ask, there is always someone who knows, right?
上網去問啊 總有人知道對不對
gather everyone's wisdom
集合大家的智慧
thus becoming a gigantic machine
因此成了一個巨大的機器
This machine is made up of people and all the machine software
這機器是由人跟所有的機器 軟體一起組成的東西
OK this is a
OK 這是一個
I'm afraid it's the biggest machine in the world.
恐怕是這個世界我覺得最大的一個機器
OK is made of all of us
OK 由我們大家來組成的
OK good
OK 好
After that there are these great
那有這些東西之後有這些偉大的
These attractive these so-called this
這些很吸引人的這些所謂的這個
Be it data science or cloud computing
資料科學也好 雲端計算也好
Great smartphone too
很棒的智慧型手機也好
is the world so good
世界這麼好嗎
Actually it's not, right?
其實不是的對不對
The world is getting scarier, right?
世界越來越可怕了對不對
He's not the only one who knows me too well
不是只有他太知道我了
And things including mine are too easy to get lost
還有包括我的東西太容易不見了
Right, like I mentioned to you guys
對不對 就像我跟各位提到的
Is your cellphone safe
你的手機安全嗎
wake up a little in the morning
有一點早上起來
What to do if your phone won't turn on
如果你手機開不了機了怎麼辦
If one day I mention to you
如果有一天 我跟各位提到
You need to check Guo Dawei's phone number
你要去查郭大偉的電話
Wow, the address book is gone
哇 通訊錄已經沒有了
My photos from the past 20 years have disappeared
我過去20年的照片已經消失了
what to do
怎麼辦
phone is not safe
手機不是安全的
You don't think your phone is safe
你不要覺得你的手機是安全的
like your pc
就像你的個人電腦一樣
it is not safe
它是不安全的
There are all kinds of malicious programs running on it
有各式各樣的惡意程式在上面跑
and more and more
而且越來越多
Everyone said, would it be safer for me to use a mobile phone from a certain manufacturer?
各位說 那我會不會用某一家廠商的手機比較安全
won't
也不會的
Anyway, some people are using it, and some people want to destroy it.
反正有人在用 就有人想去破壞
so there must be
所以一定有的
so what happens
所以哪些東西會發生
on your computer, it happens on your phone
在你的電腦上 在你的手機上也會發生
Someone will collect your sensitive information
有人會去收集你的這個敏感的資料
it will hack your phone
它會侵怒你的手機
like hacking a computer
就像侵怒電腦一樣
What about the phone? Some malicious programs?
手機呢 有些惡意程式呢
will draw your personal information
會抽你的個資
even make phone calls for you, right?
甚至幫你打打電話 對不對
Let you send text messages to friends you haven't seen for a long time
讓你送送簡訊給你很久沒有見的朋友
that it exists in a different way
那它不同的方式存在
it could be some code way
它可能是一些程式碼的方式
It is possible to go to the edge of the net to view a web page
有可能到網邊去看一個網頁
Just like you go online with a computer, you will be poisoned
就跟你去用電腦上網一樣 就中毒了
OK so this thing will happen
OK 所以這個東西會發生的
like your pc
就像你的個人電腦一樣
Your phone will have these too
你的手機也會有這些東西的
For example, something like a worm
譬如說像蟲一樣的東西
This bug-like software
這個蟲一樣的這樣的軟體
It basically takes pictures on your phone
它基本上就是照你的手機上
it just keeps on copying
它就繼續複製
Find a way to run to another phone
想辦法再跑到別的手機上
Its purpose is not to steal your stuff
它目的並不是把你的東西偷走
just run on it
只是在上面跑
In fact, it makes it happy
其實這樣它就開心了
But your phone is getting slower and slower
可是你的手機越跑越慢
Because there are still some bugs running on it
因為還有一些蟲在上面跑
because it also runs the shake time
因為它也跑搖滑時間
so slow you down
所以就把你變慢了
more than that
不只這樣子
Many people will steal your personal information
很多人它會偷你的個資
or even pawn your computer
或甚至把你的電腦當掉
collect your information
收集你的資料
Or send you an advertisement if you have nothing to do
或沒事就送廣告給你看
still can't press
還按不掉
So all sorts of things are showing up
所以各式各樣的東西都在出現
Agents refer to these malicious programs that collect your sensitive data
代為指的就是收集你敏感資料這些惡意程式
What he said is your Trojan horse program
所謂他講就是你的木馬程式
just run into your place
就跑進你的這個地方
Then remotely control your mobile phone
然後遠端操控你的手機
Of course it's the so-called milkworm
當然這是所謂的乳蟲
Just in the back, just walking
就在後面 一直散步而已
all these things
這些東西都有的
Or like you guys on a normal computer
或是說像各位在一般的電腦上
There is a so-called cookie bar
有所謂的Cookie吧
Everyone knows that when you use a browser to view something
各位知道你用瀏覽器在看東西的時候
Sometimes when you switch to different pages
有一些時候你在換不同頁面的時候
he knows you're still yours
他知道你還是你的
why does he know it's you
為什麼他知道是你
Because he wrote in some materials they sent
因為他在他們寄的一些資料
Where the data is placed is placed in the so-called cookie
資料放在哪就放在所謂的Cookie裡面
Since cookies can be placed in cookies
那Cookie既然東西可以放Cookie
can steal from the cookie, right?
就可以從Cookie偷走對不對
so what about these things
所以這些東西呢
Cookie refers to some data stored in the browser
Cookie指的是一些儲存在瀏覽器裡面的一些資料
let the site send something
讓網站寄了一些東西
Of course there are a lot of personal information in it.
那當然裡面有很多個人資料啊
Actually he could steal it
其實他可以把它偷走
OK so a lot of things to steal
OK 所以很多東西可以偷的
OK everybody say
OK 各位說
that is a personal computer but
那個是個人電腦而是
Everyone is not
各位不是啦
this was a while ago
這是上次前一陣子
done a collection of data
做過一個收集到一個資料
Of course it's okay for you to drink a bit
這當然有點你酒波沒關係
You see, in 2014 alone, there were already 650,000 malicious layers
各位看到光在2014年就已經有65萬個惡意層次了
a lot right?
很多對不對
Everyone, of course don't guess
各位當然不要猜
Don't doubt that there is more now
不要去懷疑現在還要更多
Well, everyone, these malicious levels have been installed many times.
那各位其實這些惡意層次都裝很多次了
it's just that you don't know
只是你不知道而已
We need some way to help us analyze
我們需要一些方法幫我們分析
help us interpret
幫我們解讀
can help us troubleshoot these problems
能夠幫我們排除這些問題
So we need some powerful way
所以我們需要一些厲害的方法
come to analyze
來去做分析
And the current attack is not like the previous attack
而且現在的攻擊不像是以前的攻擊
right on your phone
就在你這支手機上
where it may attack you from several points together
它可能從好幾個點一起攻擊你的地方
or from here to overweight far overweight
或從這地方再去超重遠端超重
Let's attack your phone or your system together
一起來攻擊你的手機或是你的系統
So your analysis also won't be analyzed on the same machine
所以你的分析也不會在同一台機器上分析
You will collect a lot of information on the Internet
你會在網路上去收集很多資料
look where it's coming from
看從哪邊打過來的
then you have to defend your job
那你必須要聯防你的工作
If this is knocked out, it must be able to make up for it.
這個打掉那個東西要能夠補上來
So this thing becomes more and more complicated
所以這個東西就變成越來越複雜
What do you say
那你說
It's the rest of the world's business not mine
這是世界上其他人的事 不敢我的事
Ladies and gentlemen, let me report to you that Taiwan is actually very dangerous.
各位 我跟各位報告 其實台灣是很危險的
This is the whole world they do a ranking
這是全世界 他們做一個排名
Which telecom operators are the worst?
哪一些這個電信商呢 是最慘的
OK everyone, the second place is Chunghwa Telecom
OK 各位看到第二名就是中華電信
OK ok it's 2013 of course we hope he improves
OK 好 這當然是2013 我們希望他進步了
OK, but actually, let me show you one more
OK 可是呢 其實各位再給各位看到一個
There is another miserable thing, you said that the problem of Chunghwa Telecom does not dare us to try
還有一個很慘的 你說那中華電信的問題 不敢我們試
Guys, this is another one, this is another survey
各位 這是另外一個 這是這個另外一個調查
In fact, comment control is that he manipulates your computer remotely
comment control事實上就是 他從遠端操縱你的電腦
OK, of course it means that your computer has been hacked.
OK 那當然就表示你電腦已經被攻進去了
Sorry, we are number two in the world OK
對不起 我們是全世界第二名 OK
Well, of course it's great.
好 這當然很厲害嘛
Ours is not only the top, we are the top three OK
我們這個不僅是名列前茅 我們是前三名 OK
Well Taiwan is a very interesting environment
好 台灣是一個很有趣的環境
Everyone come over here and play it OK
大家都來這邊弄一弄 OK
So it's actually very, very dangerous OK
所以其實非常非常危險的 OK
All of our stuff is constantly being infected and attacked.
我們所有的東西呢 不斷的被感染 被攻擊
ok then of course i have so far
好 那當然我到目前為止
What did I tell you?
跟各位講了哪些東西呢
I'll talk to you about the phone
我跟各位談手機
like i told you guys
就像我跟各位說
cell phone is actually
手機其實是
it represents a world
它代表的是一個世界
just like
就好像
Of course the mobile phone is very important, right?
當然手機非常重要對不對
I saw a while ago
前一陣子我還看到一個
I saw one two days ago
前兩天我看到一個
a report on tv
電視上的一個報告
Even he speaks on the Internet
甚至他網路上講
He said if your girlfriend
他說 如果你的女朋友
fell into the water with your phone
跟你的手機掉到水裡去了
Please save the water first
請問你先救水
Many people will think a little bit
很多人都會稍微想一下
Then of course you're in trouble, right?
那當然你就糟糕了對不對
It will be bad if your girlfriend finds out about you
被女朋友知道你就糟了
but what does it mean
不過這代表什麼
The mobile phone is really inseparable from it, right?
手機真的是離不開它對不對
think about it
各位想想看
In fact, we just mentioned
其實我們剛剛各位提到
mobile phone
手機呢
It actually brings us to a
它事實上帶給我們的一個
something special
很特別的東西
it's not a phone anymore
它已經不再是手機了
it's a smart phone
它是一個智慧型的手機
it represents a huge ecosystem
它代表一個巨大的生態系
behind the cloud
後面有雲端
Provide various services
提供各式各樣的服務
and through this phone
然後透過這手機
have seen the whole world
有看到整個世界
Of course my phone is not safe
當然我手機並不是安全的
In this process, there are actually many new
而這過程中其實有很多新的
ice opportunity presents itself
冰的機會出現
whatever on your phone
不管在你的手機上
or somewhere else
還是在別的地方
In fact, the world behind
其實後面的世界
bigger than your phone
比你的手機還大
there are clouds behind you
你後面有雲端
you have all kinds of services
你有各式各樣的服務
you have different scientific operations
你有不同的科學運算
in the whole back
在整個後面
They actually form a
他們其實是組成一個
a huge ecosystem on top
巨大的一個生態系在上面
of course
那當然呢
everyone knows
各位都知道
his whole thing
他這件整個所有事情
won't stop at this point
不會停在這個點上面
In fact, we will soon be in the context of the next era
其實我們很快在脈絡下一個時代
That is the so-called new era of interconnectedness
那就所謂萬物相連的一個新的時代
A new era where everything is connected
所有萬物相連的新的時代
We all know the Internet of Things
大家都知道叫物聯網
everything has to be connected
所有東西都要連接在一起
including your mobile device
包括你的行動裝置
unfortunately including your car
很不幸 包括你的車子
include your building
包括你的大樓
All sorts of things all strung together
各式各樣的東西全部串連在一起
I can't see this word anymore
這個字我已經看不太到了
Soon they estimated 50 B Company
很快他們估計有50個B連
50 billion things
50個10億的東西
to break again
要再很斷
I can't see it now
這時間點我現在看不太到了
all connected
全部連上去了
everything is connected
所有的東西連在一起了
The car is going up too
車子也要上去了
Of course, no one will doubt this matter.
當然大家也不會懷疑這件事情
right
對不對
Because in fact, there have been many reports about this matter.
因為其實這件事情已經很多在做相關的報導了
When the machine is in the next fifth generation of 5G computer
機器在下一個第五世代的5G的電腦的時候
In fact, what we have to deal with is the network that the machine is connected to.
其實要應付的就是機器連接的網路了
So the amount of data generated by machines will start to surpass
所以機器產生的資料量會開始超越
The amount of data people are using to communicate
人在使用傳達的資料量
In 5G, it is actually one of the important goals.
在5G其實就是一個重要的目標之一了
Of course these things have a purpose
當然這些東西都有一個目的的
Why we need IoT
為什麼我們需要物聯網
need these things
需要這些東西
In fact, a very important purpose is that we
其實一個很重要的目的就是我們
longing for a smart life
向往的一個智慧生活
We have a smart environment
我們有一個智慧環境
We can have a good one control at home
我們家裡可以有很好的一個控制
The air conditioner was already on when you got home
你回家的時候冷氣已經開了
when you walk too close to the tv
你走太靠近電視的時候
I want you to stand back a little
要叫你退後一點
OK
OK
then you get in the car
那你上車
In the car, you just tell him
車的時候呢 你只要告訴他說
I want to go to Academia Sinica
我想去中研院
Hey, then drive to Academia Sinica
欸 那就開到中研院
ok
ok
Hey, it sounds like
欸 這聽起來好像是
very far away
很遙不可及
In fact it's getting closer
事實上已經越來越接近了
ok everyone will see
ok 各位都會看到
Google's self-driving car
Google的自動駕駛車
Apple spends a lot of money
Apple有花很多錢
everybody is doing these things
大家都在做這些事情
Something has begun to creep in on your new
也些東西已經開始逐漸在你新的
started appearing in the car
車子上開始出現
What is included
包括什麼
i forgot which year
我忘了哪一年
The report says 2018
報告說2018年吧
He said that Toyota can do many cars
他說 Toyota很多車子都可以做
so-called distance-controlled collision avoidance
所謂的距離控制的防撞
ok
ok
So he's already started going in that direction.
所以他其實已經開始往那個方向再走
Your car has already started to go in the direction of intelligence
你的車子已經開始往智慧化方向再進行
Soon your car might be like a cell phone
很快你的車子搞不好就像手機了
ok
ok
that's not all
那不只是這樣子
Do many people use these
很多人是不是都用這些
so-called this
所謂的這個
wearable device
穿戴式的裝置
measure your sales
量你的賣波
ok know how much you walked today
ok 知道你今天走了多少
ok
ok
of course
那當然呢
not just selling wave
也不只是賣波
still look at your heartbeat
還看你的心跳
ah many many others
啊 還有很多 很多其他的
ok you today
ok 你今天
Can help you do a lot of statistics
可以幫你做很多很多統計
analyze
分析
OK
OK
So what about wearables?
所以穿戴式裝置呢
will appear in large numbers
會大量的出現
Now, everyone only sees the watch
現在呢 各位只看到手錶
And this wrist device on your hand
還有你的手上帶的這個手腕的裝置
But soon a lot of things will come in
可是呢 很快很多東西都會進來了
including with
包括跟
It has something to do with your life support
跟你的生命維持是有關係的
what's inside you
裝在你身上裡面的東西
what you wear
穿在你身上的東西
These things will start to appear one after another.
這些東西呢 會陸陸續續開始出現
OK
OK
So actually we're starting to usher in a new era
所以其實呢 我們開始在迎接新的時代
But of course you all know
不過當然 各位都知道
Everyone has seen this photo, right?
像這照片 各位都看過對不對
Everyone's waiting for something but everyone's looking at their phone
大家都在等事情 可是每個人都在看手機
right
對不對
It seems that you have seen similar photos, right?
就好像各位也看過類似的照片對不對
Everyone got this job, got this job
各位上了這個工 上了這個
after this MRT
這個捷運之後呢
Is it like this for everyone?
是不是所有人都是這樣子
OK
OK
including myself too, right?
包括我自己也是 對不對
everyone is skating
大家都在滑
OK
OK
The family seems to be slipping while sitting at the dining table
家人呢 坐在餐桌上好像也在滑
That
那
Fewer people talking in restaurants
在餐廳裡面講話的人變少了
OK everyone is typing
OK 大家都在打東西
OK, tell people how delicious my food is, take Zhang Xiang and give it away, right?
OK 跟人家講我東西多好吃 照張響送出去對不對
Well, actually, we already have a new time.
好 其實我們已經有新的時間了
this habit
這個生活習慣
And the kid seems to be starting to skateboard too.
那孩子呢 好像也開始在滑平板
OK, a lot of things have changed, right?
OK 很多東西也變了 對不對
The car is also starting to be connected to the Internet, and it will be here soon
車子也開始逐漸要連網了 很快也要到了
Is your TV not the same as before?
你的電視是不是跟以前也不太一樣呢
your smart tv this show you watch
你的智慧電視 你看的這個節目
It seems that it is not only local programs
好像也不是只有本地的節目
In fact, our new habit
其實我們新的這個習慣
have begun to emerge in our time
已經開始在出現 我們這個時代
Or even when I was a child, or what you imagine
或是說甚至我小孩的時代 或是各位想像
It's actually not the same in the next era.
在往下的時代 其實都已經不太一樣了
how do you talk to each other
大家怎麼跟對方的交談
how do you use something
大家怎麼來使用一些東西
In fact, it's not the same. OK
其實都不太一樣了 OK
So actually what I'm going to say is
所以其實我要講的是
Mobile phones are not just mobile phones.
手機呢 其實不是只有手機
Mobile phones are our window to the world
手機其實是我們通往世界的一個窗口
OK let's go through it
OK 我們透過它呢
see a lot of new things
看到非常非常多新的東西
And the whole story isn't just about the phone.
而整個故事呢 也不是只有手機
Cloud from behind Service from behind
從後面的雲端 從後面的服務
The so-called science of data, the whole of it
還所謂的資料的科學 整整它整個
underpins an idea of ​​what we call the smartphone
支撐了我們所謂的智慧型手機這樣的一個想法
So through mobile phones and other communication devices?
所以透過手機這些通訊設備呢
I'm like I just mentioned to you guys
我就像我剛剛跟各位提到
In fact, we humans have formed a
我們其實我們人類已經組成一個
a huge new machine
一個巨大的新機器
We have new and different ways to share our knowledge
我們有不同新的方式來分享我們的知識
We also have an unprecedented way of communicating
我們也擁有一個前所未有的溝通方式
you now in some way
你現在透過一些方式
you can put your thoughts in no time
你很快就可以把你的想法
soon maybe take a walk to africa
很快也許就散步到非洲去了
was not possible before
以前是不可能的
Now everything is chained together
現在所有東西是串連在一起的
as if everyone is always saying
就好像大家常常在講
how many times do you jump
你幾個跳幾次
say six times you can
譬如說六次你就可以
Can meet everyone in the world
可以碰到全世界所有的人
this was not possible before
這以前是不可能的
Of course you say
那當然各位說
can i resist this thing
我能不能抗拒這件事情
Let me tell you, don't resist
我跟各位講還是不要抗拒好了
give you a few examples
給各位舉幾個例子
Recall everyone
各位回想
The great things that have happened in the past fifty years
這五十年來發生的重大的事情
personal computer
個人電腦
appeared about forty or fifty years ago
在我們差不多四五十年前出現
what did the advent of the personal computer create
出現的個人電腦造就了什麼
It was called IBM PC and so on, which appeared at the beginning
叫IBM PC等等這一種一開始出現
Of course, it also created our IT industry in Taiwan.
當然也造就了我們台灣的IT產業
OK
OK
Of course, you can also say the other way around, who misses this opportunity?
當然你也可以反過來說那誰MISS的這個機會
Then the Internet
接著Internet
The so-called Internet of physics begins to appear
物理這個所謂的網際網路開始出現
Of course it makes a huge difference
當然它帶來巨大的變化
then you ask who is hurting on this
那你會問那誰在這上面受到傷害
After the beginning of the so-called Internet
開始有所謂的網際網路之後
How many people still write letters?
有多少人還寫信呢
few people write letters anymore
很少人寫信了
Send email to everyone
對 大家送Email
OK
OK
ok so start changing
好 所以開始改變了
Then came the so-called WallWideWeb
那出現了所謂的WallWideWeb
The so-called HTTP
所謂HTTP
I can get the data started by
我可以把資料開始透過
Web page started sending
網頁開始傳送了
OK
OK
You start to think about what has changed
你開始想想看什麼東西改變了
so-called browser
出現所謂的瀏覽器
OK
OK
How do you share your data?
你的資料分享方式呢
has changed
已經改變了
you no longer use your stuff
你不再是用你的東西
pass it on or copy it to others
把它傳給人家或拷貝給人家
Once on this so-called portal site
一上了這個所謂的入口網站
Immediately all went out for a walk
就立刻全部散步出去了
people who didn't keep up
沒有跟上的人
It's like night training is right
就好像晚訓吊對了
when searches start coming up
當搜尋開始出現的時候
Who caught up and who didn't catch up
誰趕上了 誰沒有趕上
created the emergence of Google and other companies
造就了Google等等這些公司的出現
Then mobile devices started showing up
接著行動裝置開始出現
There are many companies that have not caught up
有很多公司也沒有趕上
thus lagging behind, say, Intel
因此落後了 譬如說Intel
In this, it has lost a lot to companies like Arm
在這裡面大幅輸給Arm這些公司
Why because he doesn't know about this huge change
為什麼 因為他不知道這個巨大的改變
his past great success
他過去巨大的成功
become a huge hindrance to him now
變成他現在巨大的阻礙
Clouds start to appear
雲端開始出現了
Of course we can guess
當然我們可以猜測
Now this company is like Google, Amazon
現在這個公司像Google、Amazon
The company is up
這個公司起來了
Which companies will start to cloud weak
哪些公司會開始雲弱
So actually what I'm going to say is
所以其實我要講的是
This era is actually moving forward
這個時代其實是往前一直在推
keep going
一直在往前走
Then we may not be able to resist it
那我們可能沒有辦法去抗拒它
But we can put it to good use
不過我們可以好好來使用它
Then we must welcome the era where everything is connected
那我們必須要迎接萬物相連的時代
this is my hope
這是我的希望
one day if i could wear it
有一天我如果可以穿上它
such an internet of things
這樣的一個物聯網
such a device
這樣的裝置
this is what i want most
這是我最想要的東西
But I don't know if I can wait
不過我不知道可不可以等得到
Finally I thank the slideshow
最後我感謝投影片
many people offer me some help
很多人提供我一些幫助
Including Professor Huang Yanlan
包括黃燕蘭教授
Professor Hong Shao
洪少教授
Professor Luo Wenfeng
羅文豐教授
Professor Huo Bicheng
休比成教授
Professor Zhang Yuanhao
張元豪教授
And Dr. Yang Chuanyue
還有楊川越博士
Professor Zhang Zhewei
張哲維教授
with Professor Huang Bojun
跟黃柏君教授
I'll report it here
我就報告到這邊
thank you all
謝謝大家
thank you very much
非常謝謝
I have benefited a lot
我獲益不少
I believe that everyone here has also benefited a lot.
我相信在座的也都獲益很多
do you want to take a break or
你要休息一下嗎還是
it doesn't matter
沒有關係
Okay, let's see if there is anything else we need to ask
好 那我們看看有沒有還有要請教的地方
please
請
Hello, what I mentioned in the speech just now is
你好 在剛剛演講當中我提到的就是
data science or so-called data scientists
資料科學或者所謂的資料科學家
As far as my own understanding is
就我自己的理解是
I think he should also be classified as a basic subject
我認為他應該還上度歸類於基礎學科
The foundation grows Betal Size
基礎長得Betal Size
It should still be about how to use these basic disciplines
應該還是說如何利用這些基礎學科
So what I want to ask is to tell you what you think
所以我想請問的是說就你的想法
What do you think a so-called data scientist
你認為所謂的一個資料科學家
What basic disciplines did he use
他是運用了哪一些基礎的學科
Then how does he use it
然後他是用什麼樣的方式去用
or what proportion to use the knowledge of these subjects
或者是什麼樣的比例去使用這些學科的知識
Then he compared our current existing traditional fields
然後他跟我們現在現有的各個傳統領域的
such as physical chemistry psychology
比如說物理化學心理學
Or what is the difference between a mathematician and a statistician?
或者是數學家統計學家的區別又在哪裡
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
Data Science is actually a very
資料科學其實是一個很
sex name ok
性人的名字 ok
Represents a group of things
代表是一群東西
What about data science?
那資料科學呢
In fact, it itself is a cross-field thing
其實它本身就是一個跨領域的東西
when i talk about data science
當我講資料科學的時候呢
the question you should ask me is where is it used
你應該問我的問題是它用在哪裡
ok if you use it in the so-called manufacturing
ok 如果你用在所謂的生產製造的時候呢
At this time, the experts on the manufacturing side must come in together
那這時候生產製造的那一邊的專家必須一起進來
ok then when you ask me
ok 那當你問我說
Is this data science applied in medical treatment?
這個資料科學呢是運用在醫療的時候呢
The medical experts have to come in together.
那醫療專家必須要一起進來
then you will notice
那各位就會注意到
What is included in data science?
在資料科學裡面包含了哪些東西呢
That is to say, analyzing these data
也就是說把這些資料做分析
These scientists who sorted out these capabilities
整理這些能力的這些科學家
In addition, there are also experts in the application direction of certain fields
另外呢還有包括在做某一些領域應用方向那邊的專家
after putting it together
放在一起之後呢
to produce truly useful data science
才能夠產生真正有用的資料科學
So so overall
所以 所以整個來說呢
In fact, if we look at it academically
其實如果從學科上來說的話呢
In fact, it will be composed from different angles
其實會從不同的角度來組成
There are some words from this information project
那有一些部分的話是從這個資訊工程
such expertise comes in
這樣的專長進來
Of course, it's not just data analysis.
那當然這裡面還不只是資料的分析
or materials for learning such techniques
或資料的學習這樣的技術
If data analysis Data learning techniques
如果資料的分析 資料學習的技術
Much of it is in computer science
很多部分是在電腦科學裡面
There is a part of this following technique
有一部分這個下面的技術
is on mathematics
是在數學上面的
there's a lot of knowledge about that
那還有很多相關的知識
In fact, in different application directions
其實在各個不同的應用方向
OK so that's about all I can say
OK 所以我大概只能這麼說
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
那謝謝老師精采的演講
Since we are talking about wisdom
那既然講到智慧
Speaking of the largest machine
又講到最大的機器
Speaking of Sharing
又講到共享
Then such words
那這樣的話
What are the places where people can't be replaced?
人到底還有哪些地方是比較不能被取代的
any thoughts on this
關於這邊有沒有什麼想法
can share with us
可以跟我們分享
Thanks
謝謝
good
好
that's an interesting question
這是很有趣的問題
If the machine is so powerful
如果機器這麼厲害的話
Then what should we humans play?
那我們人到底應該扮演什麼
what kind of role
有什麼樣的角色
OK good
OK 好
Fortunately, there are still many roles to play.
不過還好目前還有很多角色可以扮演
OK
OK
But you can imagine
不過各位可以想像
There are a lot of characters starting to disappear
有很多角色開始消失了
Can you tell me which characters have disappeared now?
各位說其實現在有哪些角色已經消失了
You've noticed that some jobs in the bank are starting to disappear.
各位注意到銀行裡面有一些工作開始消失了
You often use ATM machines
你很多時候用ATM的機器
you are not very expensive
你不太靈貴
Some people are not very smart to do some materials
有些人不太靈貴去做一些資料
Do account processing
做帳號的處理
OK the way you buy a ticket has changed
OK 你買機票的方式改變了
Some parts of the semantic set are starting to disappear
語形設有些部分開始消失了
OK
OK
But there are many creative directions
可是呢 有很多創意的方向
Or new jobs are starting to emerge
或是說新的工作開始浮現了
So what I'm going to say is
所以我要講的是說
indeed in the process
的確在這個過程中
The computer starts to treat some of us
電腦開始把我們某一些
regular
經常性的
simplified work
簡單化的工作
jobs that can be easily analyzed
可以很容易分析化的工作
Structured work begins to displace
結構化的工作開始取代
But it is actually to some extent
可是它其實某種程度上來說
It also creates something new
它也創造新的東西出來了
then of course you can talk
那你當然可以談說
Are the jobs created
創造出來的工作是不是
$ less than the jobs that are currently disappearing
元少於目前所消失的工作
currently in many ways yes
目前在很多方面是的
OK
OK
you can see
各位可以看到
Today I have automation
今天我有自動化之後呢
In fact, many jobs in factories are starting to disappear.
其實工廠很多作業的工作開始消失了
because I can automate
因為我可以自動化
And it's actually more efficient doing something
而且它其實還更有這個效率在做一些事情
but you will find
可是你會發現
many things
很多東西呢
you still have to ask someone to do it
你還是得要人來做
OK
OK
For example, I mentioned to you
譬如說我跟各位提到
let me give you an example
我舉個例子來講
Let's say I want to design something
譬如說我要設計一些東西
like a cup
像杯子
these grips
這些握把
all these things
這所有的東西
In fact, many things are still done by people.
其實很多東西還是人在做的
what about the computer
電腦呢
In fact, far from the wisdom of real people
其實距離真正人的智慧
There is still a big gap
還有一個很大的差距的
Of course we think it's great
我們當然覺得它很厲害
but it's still far
可是它還是很遠的
OK
OK
let me give you an example
我舉個例子來講
Now everyone is always talking
現在大家常常在講說
I'm from a photo
我從一張照片裡面
I hope to be able to identify
我希望能夠辨認出來
is there a cat in it
裡面有沒有貓在裡面
or is there a dog laughing in it
或者說有沒有狗在裡面笑
OK
OK
Well guys it's very easy for each of us
好 那各位對我們每一個人來說是非常容易的
As soon as you see it, you'll know if anyone is in there this time.
你一看到就知道這次有沒有人是狗在裡面
You can tell if he's laughing or crying, right?
他是不是在笑 在哭 你都看得出來 對不對
But it is very difficult for a computer
可是對電腦來說是非常困難的
OK
OK
Although many people still do some so-called Deep Learning technologies
雖然現在很多人還做一些所謂的Deep Learning這些技術
Deep Learning These technologies are basically the last two stages
Deep Learning這些技術基本上它是上兩個階段
The first stage is a bit like the so-called Filtering stage
第一個階段是有點像所謂的Filtering的階段
Just how to abstract the data inside and extract it
就把裡面的資料怎麼抽象化 擷取出來
turn it into something else
把它變成另外一種東西
Then do the comparison
然後再去做比對
Let's see if the answer is
答案再看是不是
So in the process you will find it very interesting that is to say
所以在這個過程中就會發現很有趣就是說
Now you will find that there are some research findings that say
現在大家會發現在裡面有一些研究的發現說
It seems to work. I don’t know why.
好像可以用 到底為什麼 不知道
so what i want to say is
那我要講的是說
As simple as that, is there a dog smiling in a photo?
像這麼簡單 變成一張照片裡面有沒有一隻狗在笑
It's hard for a computer
對電腦來說是很困難的
It's very simple for us humans
對我們人來說是非常簡單的
OK so I'm back to these questions
OK 那所以說我還是回到這些問題
we are inside
我們人在裡面
There will always be many, many roles in it
裡面永遠會扮演很多很多角色
It's just that we'll find out
只是說我們慢慢會發現
We'll become a complementary character with him
我們會跟他變成是一個互補的角色
an interactive character
一個互動的角色
more and more like this
會越來越是像這樣出現
so many things will disappear
所以很多東西會消失
But there are many things that will be born
可是有很多東西會生出來
that's how i feel
那這是我的感覺
Hello Professor Guo
郭教授好
I feel very rewarded today
今天覺得收穫非常多
thank you for a great day
感謝您今天很精彩
My name is Lin Yuxuan
我叫做林玉軒
own background as a psychiatrist
本身的背景是一個精神科醫師
Also an amateur mobile app developer
也是一個業餘的手機程式開發者
So I would like to ask Professor Guo two questions
所以我想請教郭教授兩個問題
One is from the perspective of a psychiatrist
一個是從精神科醫師的角度問
The other is asking from a mobile development perspective
另一個是從手機開發的角度詢問
That Nature is the journal of nature
那個Nature就是自然這本期刊
There was a report of a cause two weeks ago
在兩個禮拜前有一個事業的報道
Reports say that all
報道說現今所有
mental health
就是應用在心理衛生
All apps for psychiatry
精神醫學的所有的APP
Call Pocket Spirit to make
就叫口袋精神可以使
Pocket Psychiatrist
Pocket Psychiatrist
then i believe
那我相信
I think what the professor just said is very correct
我覺得剛剛教授講得非常正確
Which means the phone has completely changed
就是說手機已經完全改變了
our new way of life
我們的一個新的生活的方式
Then I think the phone does
那我想手機確實
His new technology also changed
他的新的科技也改變了
human psychology and behavior
人類的心理還有行為
then i want to ask
那我想請教
If it is from the perspective of teaching you
如果說是從教授您的角度
and your point of view
和您的觀點來說
user experience and user interface
使用者經驗和使用者界面的
Research in the process of mobile app development
研究在手機程式的開發的過程中
heavy or not
重不重要
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
Because human behavior may be changing all the time
因為人類的行為可能一直在改變
The second is to say
那第二就是說
The main content just taught
剛剛教授主要的那個內容
Is introducing some architecture of Android
是在介紹Android的一些架構
That Android it from this 4.1 4.2
那Android它從這個4.1 4.2
There is a big breakthrough
有比較大的突破
and now to 6.0
然後現在到6.0
Then what we have been more worried about is that
那我們一直比較擔心的是說
Because of my doctoral dissertation in the past
因為過去我的博士論文
It is a service to write the background of the cell-phone
是寫用手機的背景的服務
to detect some human behavior
來偵測一些人類的行為
Then we actually all have a worry
那我們其實都有一個擔心
Worried that Android is in
擔心說Android在
while it's progressing it will look like
一直進展的過程中會像
The iOS system may put many parts of the background
iOS的系統可能把很多背景幅的部分
get it out of our reach
把它收掉到我們抓不到
Then I want to ask the professor to read this
那我想問教授看這個
A process of Android's development
Android它的發展的一個過程
Yes, because now it's like the professor said
對 因為現在就像教授講的
In fact, the protection of information security is very important
對資訊安全其實保護非常重要
I don't know what the professor thinks about this safety
那不知道教授怎麼看這個安全
There is also a disease that develops between the two
還有開發的兩者之間的病
ok let me answer the first question first
好 我先回答第一個問題
That is to say, a study of the user interface
就是說使用者界面的一個研究
It's definitely very important OK
這絕對非常重要 OK
Now everyone's most criticized
現在大家最詬病的一些
For example, a mobile phone is also good
像譬如說手機也好
or wearing a taxi or your watch
或是穿戴的士 或是你的手錶
OK, everyone thinks why the watch consumes so much power
OK 大家想為什麼手錶這麼耗電
You bring your smartwatch now
你現在帶來智慧型手錶
why so much power consumption
為什麼這麼耗電
Because the way it does it is like a mobile phone
因為它做的方式就跟手機一樣
It's what a computer's mind does
它就是一台電腦的想法在做的
the same phone
同樣的手機呢
you somehow see it
你某種程度去看它
It's doing it in a bit of an ultra-PC way
它有點超個人電腦的方式在做的
OK everyone often says
OK 大家常會說
what you see on your pc right now
你現在在個人電腦上看到的東西
Might be on the phone in a while
過一陣可能就在手機上出現
OK so what I'm going to say is
OK 那所以我要講的是
Actually this is wrong OK
其實這是錯的 OK
We go from A to B like this
我們由A到B 這樣
it's really fast
來做的確是很快
but it's basically
可是它基本上是
The logic of thinking is different
在思考的邏輯上是不太一樣
Because how people use mobile phones
因為人怎麼使用手機
It is different from using a computer
跟如果使用電腦是不一樣的
Not to mention how people use watches
更不要說人怎麼使用手錶
It's completely different from using a computer
跟你使用電腦是完全不一樣的
Let me give you an example
各位就舉一個例子
your watch keeps moving
你的手錶一直在動
I think many people have used this smart watch
我想很多人都有用過這個智慧型的手錶
It's not very useful
其實不太好用
I have several of my own and I'm fine
我自己有好幾隻我沒事都在
Because I am doing related research myself, I am using
因為我自己做相關研究我自己在使用
its interface is difficult to use
它的介面很難用
Then I'll find something to slide around
那我找一個東西滑來滑去
Sometimes I can't find what I want
有時候也找不到我要的東西
Of course the phone is the same
那手機當然也是這樣
But the phone will be better
不過手機會稍微好一點
It's at least slightly closer to your computer
它至少跟你的電腦還是稍微接近一點
So what I'm going to say is
所以我要講的是說
personal use
對個人的使用
get used to it
能對它的使用習慣
Must be able to reflect the design of your computer
必須能夠反應在你的電腦的設計上
Not only in the design of the interface
不是只有在介面的設計上
and including its operation
還有包括它的運轉上
must be done like this
也必須這樣子來做
say your watch
譬如說你的手錶
if you don't pick it up
如果沒拿起來看
Actually why do so many things
其實幹嘛做很多事情
Wouldn't it be better if you just timed it?
你就計時就不就好了嗎
There are actually things to do when you pick it up
你拿起來的時候其實有些事情才要做的
ok so our
ok 所以我們的
the way of using the habit of using
使用的方式 使用的習慣
Of course the system should do this
當然應該系統必須這樣做才對
Unfortunately that's not the case now
很不幸現在並不是這樣子
ok, why does the phone consume so much power
ok 這為什麼手機這麼耗電
Why Smartwatch Your iWatch
為什麼智慧型手錶你的iWatch
Charge every two days
每一兩天就要充電
because it's not right
因為它做法是不對的
ok, the future is actually this direction
ok 未來呢其實這個方向
Everyone is thinking about how to do new things
大家都在想怎麼去做新的東西
Especially when it comes to the Internet of Things, it should not be done like this
尤其是到物聯網的時候更不應該這樣做
when you go to the doctor
你去看醫生的時候
Maybe I'll take a bracelet home with me later
也許以後會帶個手環回家
when will you see the doctor next time
你下次看醫生的時候呢
maybe a month from now
可能是一個月後
maybe half a year later
可能是半年後
correct can't run out of power
正確不能沒電
you go home and ask everyone to take it back
你回家要所有人拿回去
Take it off and charge it
拿下來還要充電
Many people don't know how to charge, right?
很多人不會充電對不對
best time to go
最好是去的時候
The doctor took a look
醫生拿來看一看
give you another one
換一支給你
By the way, put the information in
順便資料就裝進去
ok, what can last half a year
ok 那什麼東西可以撐半年
Our current watch will never need to change the battery for a lifetime
我們現在的手錶一輩子都不用換電池
not dead yet, right?
還沒死對不對
You think what I'm going to say is right
你以為我要講的是 對
Now many designs are problematic
現在很多設計是有問題的
So this user interface follows the user's habits
所以這個使用者界面跟使用者習慣
real implementation
勢必必需要真正的實作
TALK APP IN DESIGN ON YOUR PHONE
跟應用在設計在你的手機
WATCH WEAR ARE ABOVE EVERYTHING
手錶 穿戴是所有東西上面
that's right
那才是對的入
OK this is my first question I think
OK 這是我覺得你的第一個問題
The second question is actually to say
第二個問題其實在於說
This phone is actually in the process of glasses
這個手機上面其實它的眼鏡過程中
only many things it will appear
只有很多東西它會出現
some things will disappear ok
有些東西會消失 OK
Then I want to talk about the first thing is to say
那我要講講第一個東西是說
You see the idea of ​​Android design
你看Android的設計的想法
At the bottom of it is an operating system
它最底下是一個作業系統
A so-called intermediary software is made above
上面做了一個所謂的中介軟體
It is the FriendWalk layer
就是FriendWalk這一層
why does it do this
它為什麼要這樣做
In fact, its purpose is to pull everyone in.
其實它的目的就是把大家拉進來
Many things can be placed on this layer
很多東西可以放在這一層
A field stuff comes in
A場上的東西進來
it made hardware
它做了硬體
it has something to put here
它有東西可以放在這裡
Come in on field B
B場上進來
it comes in it stuff can go here
它進來它東西可以放在這裡
So he wrapped everyone in this thing
所以他用這東西把大家全部包在裡面
OK, so everyone is roleplaying
OK 所以大家就是角色可以扮演
OK let's build this whole ecosystem together
OK 一起構築這整個生態系
OK, so the first thing that comes up
OK 好 所以這個東西出現的第一個
The basic idea is to hope that everyone can play together
基本的想法就是希望大家一起來玩
OK, so of course what if in the process?
OK 好 那當然在這個過程中的話呢
Actually there is no way to avoid it
其實沒有辦法避免了
A lot of things will leak out because of this.
很多東西就因此就會洩露出去了
because everyone knows what it looks like
因為所有人都知道長什麼樣子
OK, let's go back and say
OK 好 那就回過頭來就說
What about data protection? OK
那資料保護怎麼辦 OK
Data Protection is Now in the Cloud Era
資料保護是現在雲端時代
Everyone's most painful question
大家最痛苦的問題
You all know I went online and searched for that thing
大家都知道我上網去搜尋那個東西
or after accidentally putting something on it
或不小心把東西放上去之後
I bake shellfish all over the place, right?
我烤貝到處都是對不對
Really can't finish killing, right?
還真殺不完對不對
I don’t know where the Cache went, right?
不知道Cache到哪裡去了對不對
Google also keeps several copies
Google也留好幾份
I don't know how to get rid of it
也不知道怎麼弄掉
You still told him if you could kill me for me, right?
你還跟他講是不是可以幫我殺掉對不對
that's it
這就是這樣
So actually
所以其實呢
Now everyone is starting to think about this question OK
現在大家都開始在思考這個問題了 OK
Not just encrypting and decrypting data
不只是把資料加密解密
how can it be
怎麼能夠很
It's easy to permanently erase your data
很簡單的永久消滅你的資料
ok
ok
So this is the next important job
所以這是下一個蠻重要的工作
This work may not be possible by
這工作可能不能由
or not just should be used by android like this
或不只是應該由Android像這樣的
such an institution
這樣的一個機構
Or such a platform to do
或是這樣的一個這個平台來做
ok this is actually
ok 這個其實是
problems everyone has
大家都遇到的問題
will deal with
會去處理
Does he have something permanent
那他會不會有一些東西常駐
don't show us
不給我們看
ok
ok
My current experience is
我目前的經驗是
not so much
倒還不至於
ok
ok
ourselves on top
我們自己在上面
Modified a lot of things
修改了很多東西
did a lot of research
做了很多研究
In fact, we can still see
其實我們都還看得到
ok
ok
Generally no big problem
大致上沒有太大的問題
but what is the biggest problem
可是最大的問題是什麼呢
the biggest problem is
最大問題是
Today, for example, a manufacturer
今天譬如說有一個廠商
ok
ok
He does, for example, image processing
他做譬如說是做影像處理
so he has something
那他有一些東西呢
he will get involved
他會涉及到裡面
Modification of some things in the structure
在架構裡面某一些東西的修改
then you are scary
那你恐怖
It is not easy for him to understand this
他不容易去了解到這東西
how did it move
到底是怎麼動的
ok
ok
He doesn't want to talk to you
他也不願意跟你談
So even if that thing is over there
所以就算那東西在那邊
Actually I don't understand
其實也看不太懂
ok
ok
This is a
這是一個
when we do it ourselves
我們自己在做的時候
a problem to face
得面臨到的一個問題
still have a question
還有一個問題
that is
就是說
everything today
今天所有東西
Although open source
雖然是開放原始碼
But this guard against gentlemen is not against villains
可是這防君子不防小人
ok
ok
That is to say
也就是說呢
I made this thing
我做出來的這個東西
I will open source though
我雖然會開放原始碼
show everyone
給大家看
I can be half a year late
我可以晚個半年啊
I'll give it to you later
我會晚一點再給你啊
procrastinating
拖拖拉拉的
ok
ok
You can't get the latest version if you want to get something
你要拿東西拿不到最新的版本
like these soft hard ways
像這些軟的硬的方法
we all have some degree
大家都有某種程度
Come
來
Delay
延遲
get this thing out
把這東西能夠釋放出去
But what?
可是呢
In terms of openness
就開放性來說的話呢
exist
在
on android
Android上面
We haven't had too many problems
我們到沒有遇到太大的問題
ok
ok
big problem
比較大的問題
In fact, it should be in
其實應該是出在
this other compare
這個其他比較
mid-walled
中壁型的
make a system inside
做一個系統裡面
Those things are less available
那些東西比較拿不到
ask the director what to do
請教主任要怎麼樣
Prevent VIP Groups
防止嗨客群組
when we use that computer
在我們使用那個電腦
For mobile phones all the time
對手機一直方面
thank you all
謝謝你們
The best way is to copy
最好方法就是拷貝
ensure safety
確保安全
copy
拷貝
copy things
把東西copy
then hide it
然後把它藏起來
OK
OK
this is the best way
這是最好的方法
because i'm serious
因為我講真的
Because everything can be hacked
因為所有東西都可以被攻破的
OK
OK
The only thing that can't be broken is that you put the copy in your luggage
唯一不能攻破的東西就是你把拷貝完之後放在你家包行箱
I'm not kidding
其實我不是開玩笑的
like my own practice is
像我自己的做法是
I copied it to the hard drive after a while
我過一段時間就拷貝到了硬碟裡面
I put it away if it's important
如果很重要我就把它收起來
OK
OK
That
那
people can't get it
人家就拿不到
OK
OK
Be sure to install antivirus software.
一定要裝防毒軟體就是了
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
I have a
我有一個
doubt gold
疑惑黃金的
Now data science is actually quite popular, and there are many opportunities
現在資料科學其實已經蠻顯學,機會也很多了
Compared with this service fee, there is no boundary between people
相對於這個服務金在人的之間已經沒有界限
And always filled with more sprites
而且一直充滿了更精靈
But compared to the other part of the feeling
但是相對於另外一個感覺的部分
Even on the opposite side of Xianxue, there may be some threats
就是在顯學的相對面可能也會有一些威脅產生
Have these threats slowly turned into trends?
這些威脅有沒有已經慢慢會變成一些趨勢
It may even subvert the current ecology in the future
甚至於可能會往後程度會發生到顛覆到目前的這個生態
Have you ever thought about which of these things may have a better chance of affecting our entire life?
有沒有思考過這個東西是哪些是可能會比較有機會影響到我們整個
Now this eCos etc.
現在這個eCos等
In fact, you just mentioned this and immediately thought of the safety mentioned by the doctor just now.
其實你剛剛提這個立刻就想到剛剛這位醫師提到的安全
Security can be disrupted
安全這件事情可能會顛覆
Somewhat subversive cloud computing
某種程度顛覆的雲端計算
Because you are afraid of leaking a lot of information.
因為很多資料你都怕洩漏出去了
After you put it on, if something is not safe, you are very scared
你放上去之後如果東西是不安全的你就很害怕
At this time, it will affect everyone to use the shared storage space
這時候就會影響到大家來使用共有的那個儲存空間
So everyone feels unsafe
所以因此大家就覺得不安全
the first point
這第一點
Second point
第二點
I give an example
我舉一個例子
like myself using this search engine
像我自己在用這個搜尋的引擎
Or when using the so-called browser
或是用所謂的這個瀏覽器的時候
In fact, you also said that I have a bit of this
其實你也說我有點這個
paranoia of persecution
被迫害妄想症
OK
OK
I have several browsers
我有好幾個 browser
Actually, I don't always use one
其實我不見得常常用某一個
sometimes
有些時候是
Use Firefox sometimes Chrome I sometimes use IE when I'm happy
用 Firefox 有時候用 Chrome 我有時候高興的時候用 IE OK
because
因為
I don't want people to know too much
我不想讓人家知道太多
why do i tell him so many things
我為什麼要告訴他這麼多事情
OK
OK
Are you afraid that someone is watching you from behind?
你害不害怕有人在後面看著你
When Google Knows Everything
當Google什麼事情都知道的時候
he can sell you too
他也可以把你賣掉
OK
OK
After he can analyze it one day
他有一天可以分析完之後呢
Tell you like the Minority Report
就跟 Minority Report 一樣跟你講說
ah you
啊你這個人
what might happen
有可能有什麼可能會做出什麼事來
OK can you?
OK 可不可以
He knows you're dangerous after too many things
他知道你太多事情之後其實是危險的
OK he knows the water in your house is water
OK 他知道你家裡的水是水
OK, I know where you're flying to today
OK 知道你今天要坐飛機去哪裡
Can he guarantee that your information will not be stolen by others?
他能保證你的資料完全都不會被別人偷走嗎
It's actually hard
其實很難的
Very difficult
很難的
OK so I think
OK 所以我覺得
When you ask this question, my first thought is safety
你問這個問題我第一個想到就是安全
OK Data Security
OK 資料的安全
my second thought was
我第二個想到就是
I don't want a Big Brother watching me from behind
我不想要一個Big Brother在後面一直看著我
he knows everything ok
他什麼都知道 OK
Sometimes it's hard to think about
有時候想想蠻難受的
Although he can't do anything
雖然他也沒辦法做什麼事
I'm not afraid of him knowing
我後來沒什麼怕他知道
but weird
可是怪怪的
I'm afraid he knows everything
怕他什麼都知道
I immediately thought of these two things
我立刻想到是這兩件事情
This may cause some problems for our cloud computing
這可能會對我們的雲端計算產生一些問題
Of course you can look at it from another angle
當然你可以要從別的角度來看
For example, cloud computing
譬如說雲端計算出現
Would you say it's good for Taiwan?
你會說對台灣好不好
yet another question
又另外一個問題
OK
OK
You say we sell machines
你就說我們賣機器
We used to sell a lot of machines
以前我們賣很多機器
Everybody sell us machines
誰都給我們賣機器
Now many people don't sell us machines
現在很多人不給我們賣機器
he rents the machine
他就租機器
Are our machines sold less
我們機器是不是賣得少
OK
OK
so you can look at it from different angles
所以你可以從不同角度去看
Actually, is it good for us?
其實對我們到底好不好
in this process
這個過程中
Actually we also lost
其實我們也失去了
quite a lot
蠻多東西的
in this wave
在這一波
what did we catch
我們到底又捕捉到什麼東西
Of course it's worth it
這個當然也值得我們
look at it from another angle
又從另外一角度去看
what the hell is going on
到底是怎麼樣
I may not have fully answered your question
我可能沒有完全回答你的問題
But the first thing to think about is safety
不過先想到就是安全
It's not safe and I don't want to put things on it
不安全根本不想把東西放上去
hello thank you for your wonderful speech
你好 謝謝你精采演講
Speaking of Information Security
講到資訊安全
it must be said
就一定要講到
Actually this time Apple
其實這次Apple
impossible to open it that
不可能開放它那個
World of Terrorist Attacks
恐怖攻擊世界的資料
Of course it can take a long time
當然這件事情可以變得很久了
i want to ask
我是想請問
You develop a research scholar's perspective on a hierarchy system
你一個層次系統開發的研究學者的角度
how do you look at this problem
你怎麼去看這個問題
From our point of view
從我們的角度去看啊
If we have a way we want to break see
如果我們有辦法我們想破破看
Let's see if we can do it
看我們行不行
This of course means
這個當然就是說
From the point of view of a researcher
從做研究的人角度來看的話
Of course we would like to know about this
我們當然會想知道這件事情
If you look at it from the perspective of providing a platform
那如果從一個提供平台的角度人來看的話
Then do you feel that it is safe for you to use his system?
那你感覺你用他的系統安不安全
But of course it's like what you said
不過這當然就像你講的
there's a lot to debate
這有很多東西可以辯論
Should a manufacturer do this?
到底一家廠商該不該做這件事情
I think this may have a lot of views
我想這可能觀點蠻多的
That's actually from my own
那可是其實從我自己的
From my own research point of view
我自己在做研究的角度來看
I actually often want to know
我其實也常常想要知道說
Did this manufacturer leave a back door?
這個廠商有沒有留下後門
after he left the back door
他留下後門之後
He can do many great things
他就可以做很多偉大的事情
i don't like what he does
我不喜歡他做
OK
OK
I would also guess that
我也會猜測說
Later he said he could
後來他說他可以
I knew he had a back door
我就知道原來他有後門
OK
OK
Well of course there aren't many here
那當然這裡沒有很多
I think of many things myself
我自己就會聯想到很多事情
OK
OK
but
不過
basically i think
基本上我覺得
from this
從這個
Apple he refuses to help with this
Apple他拒絕幫這個
FBI
FBI
From the point of view of doing this
做這件事情的角度來看
actually
其實
from our system
從我們做系統
From a development point of view
研發的角度來看的話
actually i think
其實我覺得
many things can be broken
很多東西都可以破的
OK
OK
but do you know
但是你知不知道
how to break it
怎麼破而已
as if you have seen
就好像各位都看過
Turin this movie
Turin這個電影吧
oh ron fishing
Aaron Turin
during World War II
在二次大戰的時候
Break the German code
破掉德軍的密碼
It stands to reason that the encryption cannot be broken.
照理說那個加密是不能破的
but why broke
可是為什麼破了
because he knows some rules
因為他知道一些規則
every time he was in the german army
每一次他在德軍
when someone is delivering something
有人在送東西的時候
I sent some words on it before
前面都送了一些字在上面
so he knows
因此他就知道
relationship with that thing
那個東西的關係
He because of this relationship
他因為這個關係
He cracks what's behind
他就破解後面的東西
So something theoretically unsolvable
所以理論上不可解的東西
In fact, it is actually solvable
其實實際上是可解的
Back to this phone from Apple
回到Apple的這個手機
In fact, there are some secrets inside if you know
其實裡面有些秘密如果知道
Why can't it be broken?
怎麼不能破呢?
must be broken
一定能破
just didn't know it had some secrets in it
只是不知道它裡面有一些秘密
How does it do?
它東西怎麼做呢?
so everything can break
所以所有東西都能破了
i think
我覺得了
As long as things made by people can be broken
只要人做的東西就能破
It's just that I don't know the secret
只是那個秘密我不知道而已
Ask Mr. Guo
請問郭老師
Just mentioned Taiwan and information companies
剛剛提到台灣跟資訊公司
It's not as good as before the bright moon in the world
不如在世界上是明月前
So what is the main reason?
那這主要原因是什麼?
So what do you think is the solution?
那你認為有什麼解決的辦法?
Thanks
謝謝
Actually, I'm not in charge of security.
其實我不是做資安的
I saw this and I thought
我看到這個東西我也覺得
Wow how we are so honorable OK
哇我們怎麼這麼光榮OK
we are actually one
我們其實是一個
A good place to do information security research
做資安研究很好的地方
OK
OK
It's not just that there are many people on the other side wanting to hack our website
不是只有說對岸有很多人想來破我們的網站
Naturally, another big issue is
自然而然還有一個很大的議題就是
In fact, in our environment
其實在我們這個環境裡面
In fact, everyone doesn't pay much attention to law and order.
大家其實也不是怎麼那麼重視治安呢
i ask a question
我問一個問題
How many people have anti-virus software installed on their mobile phones
有多少人手機有裝防毒軟體的
Have it
有嗎
don't feel bad
你不要覺得難受
Because I didn't even pretend to be OK
因為我也沒裝 OK
In fact, many of us don't pay much attention to it.
這其實我們很多人是不那麼重視
OK so I think it has something to do with our culture too
OK 所以我覺得這跟我們的文化也有點關係
OK, it has something to do with our special environment
OK 還有我們特殊的一個環境都有關係
OK, so it’s easy for everyone to take us as a springboard to work on it
OK 所以大家在上面很容易把我們拿到當跳板在做
OK so this is
OK 所以這個是
This is what we have to be careful about
這也是我們自己得要小心的
Like I said, I talked about it for a long time, whether I am safe or not, I am not safe either
像我說我講了半天安不安全我自己也不安全
It's Teacher Guo
是郭老師
yes
是
Mr. Guo
郭老師
i want to ask
我想請問一下
Google the company
Google這間公司
because I think it's a
因為我覺得它是一間
That is a lot of companies
那個就是很多面向的公司
every company
每一家公司
Google
Google
OK
OK
because when i knew him
因為我認識他的時候
is that his Google community is very strong
就是他的Google社群非常強大
then we started to feel
後來我們開始覺得
Gmail works great
Gmail很好用
then follow him to
然後跟他到
When I start using Gmail
等我開始用Gmail的時候
He started rolling out Google Maps
他開始推出了Google的地圖
Then his map is very powerful
然後他地圖很強大
then that time
然後那個時間
almost the same
也差不多也是那個
Self-Fone
Self-Fone
social system
就是社會系統
when starting to upgrade
就開始升級的時候
Then it later became a plus operating system
然後後來變成是加作業系統
Then hit the Microsoft
然後打的那個微軟
Just because when he was PC was the beginning
就是因為他時候PC就是開始
Sample reduction
出樣減少
and now
然後現在呢
I found out that he started a business as a stationery car
發覺說他開始做企業的文器車
that feeling says
那感覺說
he is a very
他是一個非常
many oriented companies
很多面向的公司
Because he is not like other
他因為不像其他的
How Intel
怎麼Intel
he wants other companies
他想其他公司
Just focus on doing this thing
就是很專注做這件事情
And then and he's basically this
然後而且他基本上就是這個
he is in this generation
他在這個世代
and our information engineering
還有我們資訊工程
is a big change
就是大大的改變
whole society
整個社會
talk to us some what way
跟我們的一些什麼方式
That
那
i never get it
我一直搞不清楚
what is he like
他自己是怎樣的
company of
的公司
Why did he so early
他為什麼那麼早之前就
Swipe ink to make a map
劃墨力去做地圖
And how do you think he will change our lives in the future?
然後你覺得說他未來會怎樣改變我們的生活呢
OK thank you
OK 謝謝
Actually I don't know many things
其實很多東西我也不知道
If you know I'm rich too, OK
如果知道我也發財了 OK
Actually, to be honest, it's true.
其實老實說啦 是真的是這樣
When I first saw Google Map
當初我看到Google Map的時候呢
Actually, I didn't realize it at first
其實我一開始也沒有意會到
So many things can be done on it
原來在上面可以做那麼多事情
including you can do this
包括你可以做這個
Include your search in this region
包括你在這個地區性的搜尋啊
restaurant, many things
餐廳啊 很多東西
There is no way, I immediately think of a lot of work OK
沒有辦法 都立刻聯想到很多工作 OK
What about when he has a map in his hands and starts navigating?
那當他有他掌握的地圖開始做導航的時候呢
Actually didn't think of it
其實也沒有想到
At that time, it didn't occur to me that he was going to get a car.
那時候也沒有很快就想到說原來他就要弄車子
OK
OK
So this thing is actually
那所以這個東西其實
I think these companies are actually very powerful.
我是覺得這個這些公司呢其實是很厲害
Because these companies can actually guide
因為這些公司其實它可以引導
it can provide great creativity
它可以提供很大的創意
This is actually
這其實也是
i want to be like everyone
我想跟大家一樣
It is also observed that there are several very special companies
也是觀察到這些有幾家很特別的公司
Not just Google but companies like Amazon
不只是Google 包括Amazon這些公司
Or you have seen several
或是各位也看到有好幾家
Including companies like Tesla
包括Tesla 等這些公司
In fact, they are all shaping and changing our world
其實他們都在塑造改變我們的世界
Without companies like Google
如果沒有Google這些公司的話
In fact, Cloud computing will not be what it is now
其實Cloud computing 不會走到現在這個樣子
If there were no companies like Amazon
如果沒有Amazon這些公司的話
In fact, there are many things that are good for shopping
其實有很多東西那些購物也好
Or even these so-called platforms rent these
或是說甚至這些所謂的這個平台租用這些
won't go to these places
也不會走到這些地方
Of course you can also say that the time has just come
當然你也可以說時間剛好到了
But their process of leading the world and bringing these ideas
可是他們這個引領世界跟帶來這些創意的過程
It's actually pretty amazing
其實是非常驚人
I find it amazing
我自己是覺得非常驚人
Then what do you say you will go when you come down?
那你說再下來會走什麼呢
In fact, of course you all know that
其實當然各位都知道說
Coming down must be towards this very soon
再下來一定是往這個很快就
Everyone, when you see the car, it must appear immediately.
大家你看到車子一定馬上就要出現
That wearable thing is also emerging
那穿戴式的東西也正在出現中
these things will change soon
這些東西都很快就會改變
Of course there are many things that will come out
那當然還有很多東西一定會出來
So the robot stuff is pretty fast I guess
所以機器人這些東西 我想都很快
these things are very fast
這些東西都非常快
You see Google spends a lot of money doing this stuff
你看Google花了很多錢在做這些東西
His demo robot last time was actually very powerful
他上次的demo機器人其實很厲害
The robot can actually be in such an unstable state
那機器人其實他可以那麼不穩定的狀態
can walk
可以走路
that was difficult
那是很困難的
that was very difficult
那是非常困難的
Walking on snow is actually far south of walking on such ground
走雪地其實是遠南於走這樣的地上的
it's very difficult
這是非常困難的
So I don't really know what else he's going to do.
所以其實我也不太曉得他還要幹什麼
If so, you tell me I've bought his stock
如果有 你們告訴我 我已經買他股票
Thanks
謝謝
Director Guo here
郭主任 這邊
i ask two questions
我問兩個問題
The first is safety and the other is economy
第一個是安全 一個是經濟
In fact, many safe places are over-proportioned.
其實安全的很多地方是多率的
In fact, for example, technology has brought many good things
其實比如說科技帶來了很多的好的地方
I am doing information myself.
那我本身是做資訊的
From MapFriend to Mobile
從MapFriend做到手機
There may be fewer mobile phones in the future
將來可能連手機都會比較少
attached to the body attached to the body
都附在身上 附在身上
One scene is simply your ID authentication is your ears
一幕根本就是你的ID認證是你的耳朵
your face
你的臉
you can use it as a certification
就可以當來點認證
The presence of mobile phones is sometimes even more
手機的存在有時候還更會
will gradually decrease
慢慢會降低
This time an area actually
這次一個區域其實
security fact
安全事實上
There are two levels of security we're talking about
我們談的安全有兩個層次
a national level
一個是國家的層次
a personal level
一個是個人的層次
In fact, most of you now are at the national level
其實現在真正大多數你是國家的層次
That's because we have worked hard for many years
那因為以前我們做了很多年的努力
For example, IP Oracle
比如說IP Oracle
its database
它的資料庫
charge you a lot of money
charge你很多錢
We pay Microsoft every day
我們每天付 Microsoft
Now that Free Software comes out
現在Free Software出來以後
Of course you are cheaper
當然你就比較便宜
In fact we are being tried
事實上我們被努力
they are landlords
他們是地主
we are computers
我們是電腦
Write software on it every day
天天在上面寫軟體
That day Free Software came out
那天天Free Software出來
The other landlord came out again
那另外地主又出來了
then what i want to say is
那我要講的事情是
Actually the thing to say is something like
其實要講的事情就是像
after it comes out
它出來以後
The certified part of its NXRP
它的NXRP裡面的認證的部分
Its entire mechanism has been disengaged
它整個機制都已經脫離了
Credit Mechanism of Visit Master
Visit Master的信用機制
Part of its front NXRP
它的前面NXRP的部分
It's another mechanism
都是另外一套機制
Therefore, our credit basis will be based on the credit basis of payment in the future.
所以我們的信用基礎將來的信用是在建立在支付的信用基礎
Built in the CCP's database
建立在中共的資料庫裡面
So your safety I'll give you another example is to say
所以你的安全 我再舉一個例子就是說
In fact, tens of millions of dollars are stolen from our bank every year during the Chinese New Year. Everyone doesn’t know.
其實我們銀行每年 過年的時候被偷掉幾千萬 大家不知道
Then put it on to deal with it, and everyone will cover it
然後用戴上來處理 就大家都蓋過去
So every day in a safe and unsafe environment, you can actually make backups
所以每天在安全不安全的環境 其實你做備份也好
People steal things you want to see, you can definitely see them
人家偷你都要看的東西 絕對看得到
It's just whether he's driving to see, so it's a matter of safety.
只是他有沒有駕駛來看 所以安全的問題
Considering so much when someone steals information like yours from our Dao Ke
考慮這麼多 當有人向我們的道科駕去偷你這樣的資料
Or how to cheat, many technologies will be damaged
或是怎麼去騙的 那很多科技都會有損害
I must say that when this original list comes out, it will hurt him
我一定說這個原始單出來的時候 會有他的傷害
But he has a part, some people do anti-virus, and some people
但他有一部分的 有人做防毒 就有人
For example, in terms of anti-virus, maybe he is the one who releases poison, so it is 360 degrees
譬如說防毒可能他就是放毒的 就360度
We used above, for example, he made Lag or something
我們在上面就用 譬如說他讓Lag或怎麼樣有進行
So there is a good side and a bad side
所以有好的一面就有壞的一面 如幻如
I really talked about some V numbers, just like I watch VR and AR
真的講的一些V號,就像我看VR、AR
It seems to be the same as the power storage
好像跟蓄力實境都一樣
So, I think personal safety is still
所以,我覺得個人的安全還是
Some people do it safely while others do it unsafely
有人做安全就有人做不安全
Both will change
都會一體兩變
So you may be afraid of too many things and become love instead
所以可能會懼怕到太多事情反而變得愛是外甲
Like our own information security
像我們資安各自
America doesn't speak that many words yet
美國還不會談到那麼多個字
When you go to Taiwan, you have to ask questions about what to say.
到台灣變成說什麼事情要對問
Ask three passwords for everything
什麼都要問個三個密碼
I said my home address
我說我家地址
It's sign 116
就是116號跡象
That's a T
這就是一個T
All questions annoy him
全部都問得他很煩
A lot of information security has been overdone
很多資安都做過頭了
People want to see your things and want to harm your things
人家要看你東西,要害你東西
Didn't say I can't get it
沒有說拿不到
It's just too late for him to make a move
只是遲不遲得他做一個動作
I want to talk about safety or something
我想談安全的談之類
I talk about economic issues
我談的經濟問題
In fact, Ma Yun's problem has brought
其實馬雲的問題已經帶來
He sucks 450 billion a day
他一天吸的4500億
He should be able to cope with it in six months
他應六個月總共都應付出來
The whole world is sucking him away
全世界都在把他吸走
Ma Yun is a wolf who offered soldiers and said he was a disaster
馬雲是一個狼獻兵說他是個災害
OK, the Chinese Communist Party is also guarding against it now.
OK 那中共現在也在防 也防著它
In fact, it has brought about 30% to 50% of the bank
實際上它帶來的已經有大概三到五成的銀行
Will not exist in the future will be dumped
將來不存在會倒掉
The bank is not that big in the office
那銀行也不會那麼大辦公室裡面
blow air conditioner a lot of sailors
吹冷氣很多航員
it will become a small office
它會變成一個小的office
So what I'm going to talk about is
那這些我要談的事情就是說
A lot of manpower is released
很多的人力release出來
Last year, the channel brought about one million stores in mainland China
通路上帶去年大概大陸到百萬家店
Not on the big market, on the middle market
大盤上中盤上都不見
So the problem in the future is a polarized problem
所以將來問題是兩極化的問題
rich people are rich
有錢的人是很有錢
no money is no money
沒有錢是還沒有錢
So from twenty two you can have
所以從二十二可以要
There are so many careers to find a job
事業這麼多要找到工作
Almost everything below is doing building work
幾乎下面都是做樓位的事情
The middle is all braked
中間全部被制動化
Replace all three words
三個字全部替代
Whether traffic braking
不管是交通制動化
Foley Brake Chemicals
福利制動化工廠公司
almost no one is there
幾乎都沒有人在
Then the economic problem at this time
那這個時候經濟的問題
There is a problem of decoupling from the currency
就出現一個跟貨幣脫鉤的問題
that capital is rich
那資本很有錢
For example, today I met a
比如說我今天碰到一個
For example, today we do venture capital
比如說我們今天做創投
I haven't had a day
我一天沒
There are 20 households losing 5 million each
每家丟500萬就有20家
I am the major shareholder of each
那每家我是大股東
Then account for those VC
然後賬那些VC
What is the bed Startup Brainpower
就是什麼床 新創公司腦力
The start-up is working under the account
那新創公司在賬下面勾工
Then he always takes the most money
那他永遠在收最多的錢
Therefore, in the future, the relationship between the United States and the CCP
所以將來美國跟中共的
They have money and shout more at the top
他們那邊有錢喊多在上面
I think we have a problem with the problem
我想我們針對問題有問題
In fact, it means
其實就是說
The economy will bring about the next
經濟將會帶來下一段
The next phase of the revolution
下一階段的革命
what's your opinion
你的看法是怎麼樣
Because in fact too many careers
因為實際上太多事業
Too many poor people are enslaved
太多的窮人被奴役
Two phases
兩期化
This time the power of the times is actually a rebound
這一次時代力量其實是一個反彈
Then this must be an economic issue
那這個經濟一定要的問題
more dangerous
安全更危險
Thanks
謝謝
I think indeed
我想的確
this new economic era
這個新的經濟時代
New technology will definitely bring about new changes
新的科技一定會帶來新的變革
This is for sure
這是一定的
ok
ok
What about the process?
這過程呢
In fact, as we just mentioned
其實就像我們剛提到
something will disappear
有些東西會消失
some will appear
有些會出現
ok
ok
that as
那作為
From the perspective of this research
如果從這個研究的角度來看
or from an educational point of view
或是從教育的角度來看
In fact, we have to get used to these things very quickly.
其實我們必須要很快去適應這些東西
know what the future might hold
知道未來可能會怎麼樣
OK
OK
How can we bring our students
我們能夠怎麼能夠帶給我們學生
And bring to our society the public
還有帶給我們這個社會大眾
what a warning
怎麼樣的一個警訊
or what should be done in research
或是在研究上應該做哪些東西
I think it's hard to do
我想這個很難去做
OK
OK
And this thing is international now
而且這東西現在是跨國了
The problem is actually very, very complicated
問題其實非常非常複雜
I also agree
我也同意說
In fact, you can't be afraid of everything
其實也不能夠什麼都害怕
If you say you want to be completely 100% safe
你如果說要完全100%安全
It is actually difficult
其實是難的
It is always a principle of proportion
這永遠是一個比例的原則
where can it be done
能夠做到哪裡
you think it's ok
你覺得是可以的
where should it be done
那應該做到什麼地方
Some places may adopt a more conservative approach
那有些地方可能是採取比較保守的做法
some places may compare
有些地方可能比較
the money
這個錢
This compares to the previous one
這個比較往前這個
Don't think about these things compare this
不去想這些東西比較這個
can't talk about money
不能講錢在
It's basically a way of pushing forward
它基本上是比較往前推的方法
In fact, there are different strategies in it.
其實這有不同的策略在裡面
so i agree
所以我也是同意
There is a consideration like
有像這樣的一個考量
good
好
I think it's almost time
我想時間也差不多了
Thank you so much today
今天非常非常感謝
My master's wonderful speech
我主人 精采的演講